<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatyse of ye ryght honourynge and wourshyppyng of our sauiour Iesus Christe in the sacrame[n]t of breade and wyne when it is ministred wyth thankes geuing at the holy supper: sette forth by Rycharde Bonner priest, in ye yeare of our lord god. M. CCCCC xlviii. and the .xii. of Nouember.</title>
            <author>Bonner, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3287</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110945</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846393</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846393</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11356</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16370)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11356)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 28:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatyse of ye ryght honourynge and wourshyppyng of our sauiour Iesus Christe in the sacrame[n]t of breade and wyne when it is ministred wyth thankes geuing at the holy supper: sette forth by Rycharde Bonner priest, in ye yeare of our lord god. M. CCCCC xlviii. and the .xii. of Nouember.</title>
                  <author>Bonner, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[176] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[N. Hill] for Gawlter Lynne dwellyng on somers kaye by Byllynges gate],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1548.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L (L8 blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks leaves D2,3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11356:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11356:1"/>
            <p>A treatyſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght honourynge and wour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppyng of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſte in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of breade and wyne, when it is mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred wyth thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing at the holy ſupper: ſette forth by Rycharde Bonner prieſt, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare of our lord god. M. ccccc xlviii. and the .xii. of No<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uember.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iohn .iiii.</bibl>
               <p>The houre cometh &amp; is nowe when trwe worſhippers, ſhal worſhip the father in ſpirit &amp; veryte, for the father ſeketh ſuche, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may worſhyp hym.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of N. Hill, a compartment with the blazon or coat of arms of Queen Mary I at the base, the winged female personification of Victory seated with a palm branch and laurel wreath at the top, the female personification of Justice standing with a sword on the left, and the female personification of Prudence standing holding a snake by the neck to the right (not in McKerrow)</figDesc>
                  <head>
                     <q>DIEV ET MON DROYT</q>
                  </head>
                  <p>VICTORIA</p>
                  <p>IVSTITIA</p>
                  <p>PRVDENTIA</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11356:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11356:2"/>
            <head>To the ryght re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerende father in God / Thomas, archebyſſhop of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, and of all Englande Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politane, Rycharde Bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner wyſſheth grace and peace in our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt, wyth the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of all godly knowledge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N aſmuch, ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght vertuous father, as god hath not onely called you for longe (as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men haue wel perceiued) to ſuche a knowledge of hys mooſt holy worde, as dyd ſtyrre vp in you both a great reuerence towardes the ſame, and cauſe you ryght earneſtly
<pb facs="tcp:11356:3"/> to deſyre to haue it trewly taught &amp; ſet forth to the glory of god in al pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, but ſpecially amongeſt vs hys people, of thys your natiue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey: but hath alſo, after it hath now plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed hym to offre the ſame frely vnto vs, called you to haue the ouerſight therof, I haue thought it not onely mete, but therwythal my bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de dew tye to preſent thys my poore worke vnto your faythful dyſcretion. And not bycauſe I dyd eyther iudge any thynge to be in it whych I wolde de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare vnto you, as yf you were igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſame, or els that I feard you wolde not prouyde (as much as in you laye) the trewth in al thynges to be knowen and ſet forth wythout the vtteryng of my rude and ſymple mynde in it: but onely bycauſe I, knowyng the ſlenderneſſe of my ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, and beyng yet conſtrayned to wryte of thys ſo weyghty a matter, feared that there might be ſumwhat
<pb facs="tcp:11356:3"/> wrytten of me in it, that ſhoulde not fully agree w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the veryte of goddes worde, which is now ſo greatly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red almoſt of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſincerely de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared, that it ſemeth they wold euen deuoure the ſame, yf they myght but ones ſpye it out. I haue therfore hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly gyue this poore worke vnto you inſpecially, that it myght rather be corrected by your godly iudgement and dyſcrete ouerſyght, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thought worthy to be thankefully receyued. And leſſe the rudeneſſe therof might yet let you from the reading of it for the ſame, I haue here alſo, in a brefe ſumme, ſet forth the ſpecial matters of it, whych are theſe.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt, in declaryng how our Lorde Ieſu Chriſte myght be honoured a ryght in thys ſacrament, when it is myniſtred at an holy ſouper, I haue ſhewed what God gyueth vs by his holy worde and ſacramentes, &amp; ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally what he gyueth vs by this moſt
<pb facs="tcp:11356:4"/> holy ſacramente of hys bodye and blode, by the whiche I haue ſayde, that our lorde Chriſte, (though tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe his heauenly ſpirite alſo) of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth and preſenteth vnto vs hys very body and blode, as it was both in ſufferynge death for vs here and as it is alſo at the ryghte hande of God for vs nowe, that is to ſaye, as his very bodily Paſſion &amp; trew Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and Aſcenſyon, was and is continually the onelye meanes that purchaſeth vs the grace and good wyll of God for the remyſſion of all our ſynnes, and preſenteth the ſame freely vnto vs by hys mooſte mighty ſpirite &amp; by this his holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente, for to helpe vs bothe to a ſure fayth and truſt in the ſame free remyſſyon, and for to woorke in vs alſo all the hole ſtrength and vertue of his very body and blode: as the very ſame mekeneſſe, loue and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte with al the holynes, ryghtuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:11356:4"/> and purite that hath alwayes bene and is in it. Theſe .ii. thynges chiefely doth our lorde Ieſus Chriſt offer and freely preſent vnto vs by hys myghtye and mooſte heauenly ſpirite and by thys holy ſacrament, to thentente that we myghte ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue by the vertue of hys bodelye paſſyon, whyche he ſuffered yet but once for all, the free remiſſion of our ſynnes at all tymes, and by his trew reſurrectyon and aſcenſyon our full iuſtificatyon: lyke as he hathe dyed for the one aſwell as for the other. By meanes wherof I haue ſayd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that thys ſacrament is called the bodye and blode of Chriſte, and the very teſtament or promyſe of theym beyng preſent with it thus, at al ſuch times as it is miniſtred according to his inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue in lykewyſe further declared, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuche as there is preſent thus the bodye and blode of Chriſt, ſo muſte
<pb facs="tcp:11356:5"/> this nedes be the honoure and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe ſpecially dew vnto it when it is miniſtred. That we do fyrſte and before we wyll receyue it, beyng the treaſure of all heauenly vertues, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue ſuche a fayth and truſt in hys bodyly paſſyon and trew reſurrecty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thorow this his free and vndeſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued callynge of vs to the better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of it by thys ſacrament of hys owne inſtituting for the ſame purpoſe, as maye cauſe vs both to laye awaye all the vyces within our corrupt bodyes with ſuche a repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce as feleth vs ſumwhat to haue nede of the greate vertues of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in it, and to beleue alſo that we ſhall the more aſſuredly receyue then the full remyſſyon of all oure ſynnes thorow the worthines of the ſame paſſion and reſurrectyon.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we do forth with vp on thys callyng of vs vnto faith by thys ſacrament, receyue it externally
<pb facs="tcp:11356:5"/> alſo accordyng to hys ordinance, for the ſtrengthenyng &amp; confyrmyng of the ſame fayth the more aſſuredly in vs, and for our better encreaſyng in his moſt godly vertues. And third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that we from thence forth do geue ouer oure ſelues holly to the reſt of hys lawes, but ſpecyally to the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable and louyng expreſſing of his mekeneſſe and pacience to oure ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghboures agayne, lyke as he hathe moſte gentely dealte with vs in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng theym vnto vs freely before. Theſe .iii. thinges, repentance, faith, and amendemente towardes oure neyghboure, are the ſpecial honours dwe vnto thys ſacrament at all ſuch tymes as it is miniſtred accordynge to his ordinance, wherwith we muſt honour it in ſpirite &amp; verite. And yet do not theſe kindes of honouring it, let y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhold not at al ſuch times as we wyll receyue it, humbly honoure it with all the powers and membres
<pb facs="tcp:11356:6"/> of our bodyes alſo (yf ſome neceſſitie do not debarre the ſame) as with the vncoueryng of our headdes, wyth the knelyng and bowyng downe of our bodyes, and with the prayſyng of hys goodnes therein with oure tounges: but the honouring of it in ſpirite and veryte doeth ſeclude all other tokens to be done vnto it, but when we can ſo wourſhyppe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. As to wete: we can neuer ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure thys ſacramente a ryght with handes and knees, but when we can fyrſt conceiue ſuch a fayth and truſt in the bodylye paſſyon and trew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectyon of Chriſte for the remyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of our ſynnes, by hys free cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of vs vnto it thorow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng of thys his ſacrament to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally receyued in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of the ſame, as cauſeth vs both to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of our former ſynnes, and to be redye and glad to receyue it alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to hys ordynaunce for the
<pb facs="tcp:11356:6"/> better aſſuraunce of the ſame fayth in vs. The whiche fayth as we can neuer conceiue it by thys ſacrament, but onely when it is preſented to be externally receyued accordynge to Chriſtes ordynaunce (for hys ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce in it and in al other thynges is the onely thing that cauſeth vs to gather a ſure fayth in hym) ſo is it then onelye to be wourſhypped ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally alſo, and at none other tyme.</p>
            <p>And thyrdely I haue ſhewed by a plaine declaratyon taken bothe out of the holy ſcripture and of the vſe of the prymatiue churche, that there ſhould no meſſe be done wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſouper of the Lorde is hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, without communicantes, that is to ſaye, without ſuche as maye haue the ſacrament communicated vnto them. And that thys is trew, ſayncte Cyprian ſpeakyng of the ryghte v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of the lordes ſupper ſayd alſo,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:7"/> in wrytyng of it thus: <hi>uti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ille ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos uice Chriſti fungitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. ii. Epiſt. iii</note> 
               <hi>qui id quod Chriſtus fecit, imitatur.</hi> That is to ſaye, that prieſt doubtleſſe doeth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the office and doing of Chriſt in thys ſacrament, that doth folowe euen the ſame thyng, whiche he dyd in it. Nowe yf that prieſt do execute the offyce and doynge of Chriſte a ryght, that foloweth it only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt hym ſelfe dyd in it, then do not thoſe prieſtes vſe thys ſacrament a ryght that wyl not entende, when they wyl holde the ſouper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, to ſtyrre vp a trew fayth in Chriſt for the fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remyttyng of all ſynnes and for the conferrynge of all other vertues, by the offerynge of it to be receyued ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally, and that wyth the gyuyng of ſuche thankes, thorow the recy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great goodneſſe of god ſhewed forth in oure ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt, as may quicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the people both a ſure fayth in Chriſt and alſo
<pb facs="tcp:11356:7"/> a reuerence towardes hys ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or euer they ſhall receyue it: but wyll make them beleue eyther that they ſhall receyue as muche profyte yf they do but loke vpon the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as God hath ordeyned to put into theyr myndes by the corporall eatynge and drynking therof, or els that they ſhal take as muche profyt yf they do receiue it but in one kynd onely, as they ſhuld yf they dyd take it in both.</p>
            <p>And fourthly I haue declared that it ought to be muche reproued in a trew chriſten man, to be preſent at the holy ſouper of the Lorde, and not to receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament. Bycauſe the doynge therof muſte nedes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede of the imperfection of fayth: as eyther bycauſe men do not beleue theſe wordes a ryght when they are ſpoken vnto them: take, eate, take, drynke, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do not eſteme dere ynough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> healthfull meate &amp; drinke
<pb facs="tcp:11356:8"/> of hys body and blode, or elles they haue ſome ſuperſtitious feare of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, in thynkyng them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre a ful perfection of lyfe to be in vs before we ſhoulde receyue them, when they requyre none other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to be in vs then that we wyll but ones deſyre vnfeynedly to haue oure imperfection and weakeneſſe ſtrengthened by ſuche thynges as they frely offre vs to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame with all. Now whyche of all theſe thre do holde a man from receyuyng of the ſacrament, it is doutleſſe worthye great reprofe.</p>
            <p>Theſe foure thynges ſpecially, dere father, haue I declared in thys lytle worke, and for the better profe of them to be as they are here decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (as it ſemeth to my poore iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) I haue alſo confuted ſome of the principall argumentes, whyche the Pope, thorowe hys adherentes,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:8"/> was wont to make for the contrary. Moſte humbly deſyryng your good lordſhippe now, that yf there be any thyng in it whych do not agree with the veritie of goddes worde, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyſhe me of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, that it might ſo thorow your godly correction, at the leaſt way do not hurte, though it be lyke to do but lytle good. Which thynge yf it myght pleaſe you of your goodneſſe to do, I woulde not onelye retracte and wyth all dyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence reuoke agayne all ſuche faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes as your diſcretion ſhall fynde in it, but alſo thynke my ſelfe bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to praye for your good eſtate ſo longe as my lyfe ſhoulde endure. The whyche I beſeche the lyuynge God, thorowe hys dearely beloued ſonne Ieſu Chriſte longe to continue, to the glorye of hys moſte holy name, and to the profyte of your ſoule.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>And thus moſte hartely fare ye wel.</salute>
               <pb facs="tcp:11356:9"/>
               <date>Wrytten the ſeconde yeare of the reygne of our ſouerayne lorde kyng Edwarde the ſyxte, and the xiiii. of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre. </date>
               <signed>by Your obedyent Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſen and dayly orator Rycharde Bonner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:11356:9"/>
            <head>¶ Of the right honouring and worſhyppyng of oure ſauiour Ieſu Chriſte, in the ſacrament of breade and wyne, when it is miniſtred at the holy ſouper.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the good and ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple might haue a grounded &amp; ſure enſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this, it ſhal be expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for them to know fyrſt what honouryng and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyng in the ſcripture, is called, and is, and wherin the trew honouring of our lorde Ieſu Chriſt doeth ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſyſt and ſtande. Out of the whiche then it ſhall be eaſye to perceyue howe we ſhoulde honoure Chriſte a ryghte in thys holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11356:10"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardeli, what it is.</note>Nowe to honoure or worſhyppe, (as it is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> outwardly) is to ſhew vnto one, whome we wyl honoure, tokens of a good wyll and mynde, and of hauynge hym in eſtimation and reuerence in oure hartes. As to prayſe hym wyth wordes, to knele or fal downe before him, in ſhewing him obedyence therewith, or els to gyue hym ſuche gyftes as we iudge him to haue moſt pleaſure in. All theſe be outward tokens of a good wyll and mynde within, and of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge one in eſtymatyon and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in our heartes. Therefore to whome ſo euer we do ſhewe theſe tokens, there doeth euery man ſaye, that we do honour and wourſhippe him therwith.</p>
            <p>But as they are oftentymes of dyuerſe condytyons or ſundrye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees amongeſt vs, vnto whom we do thus ſhewe honoure and wour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe, ſo do we vſe dyuerſe and
<pb facs="tcp:11356:10"/> ſundry tokens alſo in honourynge them. For they that be our ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, are otherwyſe honoured of vs, than they that are ether oure inferyours or lyke vnto vs. And lykewyſe do we honoure theym alſo that are oure hyghe gouernours, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe than them that are not in ſo hyghe authoryte. For ſome do we honour only with the puttyng of of our cappes, other ſome with cappe and knee, and other ſome agayne with knelyng hole downe, with kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of theyr handes, and ſuche like. And yf we wyll honour any manne wyth gyftes, ſo are the ſame diuerſe wyth vs alſo. For moſte commenly we wyll geue vnto euery man ſuche kynde of gyftes as we knowe to be mete for hym, and as we thynke he wyll thankefully take. As to great men do we geue great giftes, and thoughe not great in coſte and value, yet coſtly in beyng according
<pb facs="tcp:11356:11"/> to their pleaſures. And to honoure men thus doeth euen naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon learne vs: whyche teacheth, that for aſmuche as honouryng muſte be a ſhewynge of a ſynguler good wyll and mynde, &amp; of hauyng one in reuerence in our hertes, ſo muſte we haue a great reſpecte both to the dig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite, and to the wyll and pleaſure of the perſone alſo, whome we wyll ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure either with oure bodyes or gyftes. Wherupon it commeth, that yf we perceyue them, whome we wil honoure with gyftes, to haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in huntynge, we do rather geue them ſweft greye hundes, than good drawyng oxen. Haue they pleaſure in halkyng, ſo do we ſoner geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſparre halke, than the beſte ſyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng byrde that can be gotten. And thus doubtleſſe do we in al our gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, we haue alwayes our chiefe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte to the delyte and pleaſure of him, vnto whome we will ſhewe our
<pb facs="tcp:11356:11"/> ſelues beniuolent and thankefull.</p>
            <p>Nowe ſeyng than that euery na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture learneth vs thus to honoure euery manne, accordynge to it that we holde of his dygnite, and to haue a ſpecyall reſpecte alwayes to the delyte and pleaſure of hym whome we wyll honoure wyth gyftes or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thankfulneſſes: and that Chriſt oure ſauiour, is the hygheſt in all degrees, and therwythall of ſo great dygnyte that we neyther haue nor can get of oure ſelues it wherewyth we myghte honoure hym accordyng to hys degree, and as we of dewtye are bounde: ſo muſte we, ſpecyallye in the honourynge of hym, haue a greate reſpecte vnto it, wherein he wyll be honoured of vs, and what maye be to hym pleaſaunte and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable.</p>
            <p>Yf we wyll then loke vpon the holy ſcripture aryghte, oute of the whyche onely, we may be in certeine
<pb facs="tcp:11356:12"/> of thys, ſo do we fynde that oure Lorde and God requireth thys ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure of vs ſpecyallye:<note place="margin">What y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouryng of God is and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpecial tokens thereof.</note> fyrſte that with al our hertes &amp; mindes we geue fayth vnto al his wordes &amp; workes: and ſecondly that we freli and to the prayſynge of his name &amp; enlarging of hys kyngdome, confeſſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the ſame fayth outward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, with the geuynge of our holely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes to the exercyſynge of all his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and commaundementes: as to the hearyng of his worde deſirouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to the receyuynge of his ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes thankefully, and to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyenge of our ſelues humbly to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng, prayer, and to all the dedes of charytie: that our bodyes therwith, myght be kept vnder, and gentelye ſerue both hym &amp; our neyghbour in all holyneſſe &amp; ryghteouſnes. This is the true honouryng of oure lorde God, &amp; the ſpecyall tokens thereof. Vnder the whiche theſe tokens are
<pb facs="tcp:11356:12"/> alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended, both that we with our bodyes do ſhewe all humylytye and mekenes when with our ſoules we perceyue the grace of God to be ſpecially preſent vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Other toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the trew honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of god.</note> as it is in the miniſtracion of hys worde and ſacramentes, &amp; alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we prouide his worde to haue a place &amp; tyme appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted conuenient for the honourable miniſtracion therof, &amp; his ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to haue inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes both honeſt &amp; ſeming. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe latter toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are alſo a kynd of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honourynge of God, may wel be ſene by them of the olde tyme, vnto whome he gaue com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the decent myniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon of his holy word and ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, both that there ſhould be buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, fyrſt a coſtly tabernacle, &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a gorgyouſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an alter, &amp; al ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhould be prouided many inſtrumentes of golde, ſyluer, precy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe ſtone, of ſylke, cypres &amp; ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of religion, &amp; let
<pb facs="tcp:11356:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:11356:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:11356:14"/> it be an acceptable thynge vnto hym that they ſhoulde honour him wyth the fallynge downe before the Arke of promyſe,<note place="margin">i. Re. ii.</note> and towardes the ſame, as alſo towardes heauen, to lyfte vp theyr handes and eyes, for the ſhewynge of theyr obedience towardes hym therewyth: becauſe men ſhoulde the more ſurely know, hys grace to be ryght preſent, at the myniſtracion of all ſuche thynges as he had ordeined hymſelfe, to geue forth the ſame by, and that the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of them was therfore right preciouſe and honourable.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gal. iiii</note>But ſeyng theſe thynges are nowe out of vſe, (as towchynge to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commaundemente of God whereby they had a ſacramentall ſignification) to wete, both temple, ceremonyes, and alſo the inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes vſed for the ſame: and that the lorde in the newe teſtament hath ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poyncted neither temple nor inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:14"/> lyke as there was in the olde, but dyd bothe he hym ſelfe, and hys Apoſtles alſo after hym, vſe euerye commen houſes at theyr aſſemblyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges together and when they woulde yet preache the word of lyfe, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte euen commen inſtrumentes for the myniſtration of ryghte holy ſacramentes: we maye well gather therby, both that he wyll be aſwell preſent with vs nowe, beyng gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together in his name, eyther to heare hys moſte lyuely worde, or to vſe hys moſte holy ſacramentes, or to do any other Godly exercyſe els, as he was before, in what place ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be, and wyth what kynde of inſtrument ſo euer his holy religion be vſed or ſette forth: and alſo that the grace geuen vs by hys holy wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and ſacramentes nowe, doth chief<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly call vs to the diſpiſinge of al plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaunt worldly thynges, and wyll vs to remembre onely thynges heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:11356:15"/> &amp; permanent. Out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche it doeth alſo folow, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeing he hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement nor ſhewed exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple him ſelfe, nor none of his apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles after him, that we ſhould ſhewe vs to worſhyp hym or hys relygyon with the buyldyng of gorgious tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples, or with the preparyng of golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſtrumentes for the miniſtratyon of hys holy ſacramentes, ſo can ther no man ſaye, that the buyldynge of gorgyouſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, or the preparinge of goodly inſtrumentes ſhoulde be any of the ſpecial tokens of the true honouryng of God or of hys holy re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lygyon, more than euen very ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and playne. And in lykewyſe, ſeing that he hath nether geuen com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement nor ſhewed any enſam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple that we ſhould now ether lift vp handes or eies, or knele down to his holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, lyke as they did in the olde teſtamente, but did hold the moſt deyntye feaſt of hys holy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb facs="tcp:11356:15"/> with his diſciples as they were ſytting at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table, according to their accuſtomed maner, ſo can there no man appoynte theſe thynges to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteyne ſpecyally to the honouring of god in his moſt holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.</p>
            <p>Yet ſeyng God is euen of the ſame ſpirite and mynde towardes man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde nowe that he was then in the olde time,<note place="margin">Hebrue. xiii.</note> and that he doth geue vs euen the ſame thing now by his holy word and ſacramentes,<note place="margin">i. cor. x.</note> that he then gaue forth vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea and that ſo much the larger doeth he geue them vnto vs now as Chriſt hath opened al thynges more plainly by his com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myng into our nature corporally: it muſt nedes therfore be a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo of hauing him in honor &amp; reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce now aſwel as it was the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both to prepare an honeſt place &amp; inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better vſing of his word &amp; ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; alſo w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des &amp; knees applyed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble mekenes of the
<pb facs="tcp:11356:16"/> ſpirite, to receyue the ſame with all reuerence, when ſo euer they ſhall be myniſtred vnto vs. But bycauſe the humble mekeneſſe of the ſpirite one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, muſt appoint in euery man, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and howe farre forth theſe thynges ſhall be tokens of the trew honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of God in his holy word and ſacramentes, (and not bycauſe they belonge vnto it ſpecyally of them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues) ſo wyl I fyrſt declare what thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges God geueth vs nowe by hys holy worde and ſacramentes, that the ſpecial honour due vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame myghte the better be knowen, as the only meanes which may cauſe theſe other kyndes to haue place wyth theym alſo.</p>
            <p>What tyme as oure ſauyour Chriſte ſhoulde offer vp hys bleſſed body vpon the croſſe for the redemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of mankynde,<note place="margin">i. Io. ii. Ephe. v</note> he dyd it with ſo muche mekeneſſe, loue, and charitie, that the heauenly father was fullye
<pb facs="tcp:11356:16"/> therwith content and pacified: right thankefully accepting the ſame into his diuine nature, as a meane moſt ſufficiente &amp; fullye able for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng in all men not onely of a ſure fayth &amp; truſt in the remyſſyon of all theyr ſynnes,<note place="margin">i. Ti. ii. Heb. ix.</note> but for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workyng al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of all holynes &amp; righteouſnes in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For fyrſt, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was the bleſſed bodye of hys derely beloued ſonne whiche was ſo offered vp vpon the croſſe, he ſawe it to be able ynoughe for the workynge of a ſure fayth in all men, and to cauſe theym to truſte vnto the worthynes of it for the full remyſſyon of their ſynnes, how ſore ſo euer thei had offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, or how long ſo euer they had lyen therin. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, in that it was done with ſo muche mekeneſſe, loue, and charite as dyd excede all other in plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, he ſawe it able ynough to make all men partakers of thoſe his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly vertues: both for the ſtablyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing
<pb facs="tcp:11356:17"/> of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſame faith againſt al ſuch ſinne as deth &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuel might laye agaynſt them afterwarde, &amp; for to be as a ſure earneſt vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo, whiles they wer yet in this world, of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> godli life, which thei might hope to receiue more fully in another world.</p>
            <p>Mooſte thankefully therefore dyd the infynite goodneſſe of God accepte and take the meke paſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and louyng death of oure ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſu Chriſte,<note place="margin">Epheſ. i. Hebre. ix</note> that man thereby myght not onely be iuſtyfied, but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo be holly reconſylled and brought agayne vnto hys fyrſt ſtate of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, that is to ſaye, that he myght not onely be looſed and quit fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hys ſynnes committed thorow fayth con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued in the worthy acceptyng of hys paſſyon, but receyue thorow the ſame fayth alſo ſuche a parte of hys ful and aboundant mekeneſſe, loue, and charite, as myghte both recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyle and brynge hym agayne to the
<pb facs="tcp:11356:17"/> ryght expreſſyng of this his Godly ymage vnto other, and alſo put him in a ſure hope whyles he were yet in thys lyfe, of the full receyuynge of theſe heuenly vertues in another lyfe.</p>
            <p>And althoughe oure moſte mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull ſauyour, of hys omnipotente wyſedome, knewe well ynoughe, his meke paſſyon and louynge deathe ſhoulde ryghte thankefully thus be accepted and taken into the dyuine nature of hys heauenly father, as a thynge moſte ſufficiente and fullye able to be the onely meanes of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſaluation, and that man ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhoulde fynally be ſaued:<note place="margin">Bycauſe of oure weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, were the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned.</note> yet forbycauſe he ſawe the weakeneſſe of manne to be ſuche that he would be verye ſlacke in geuynge faythe to thys gladde tydynges of the worthye acceptynge of hys paſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, eyther for the contynuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſyon of hys ſynnes, or for the
<pb facs="tcp:11356:18"/> receyuyng of hys aboundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t grace to amende them alwayes againe, yf the effecte of the ſame hys paſſyon and onely meanes ſhoulde alwayes be brought and preſented vnto him, only thorowe the ſecrete inſpiration of God: ſo dyd he moſte mercyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye therfore inſtitute and ordeyne, before he ſhoulde ſuffer, certayne ſygnes and tokens, to cauſe al them, vnto whome he ſhoulde peculyarly, and more than to all other nations, ſende or geue the ſame, to truſte ſo muche the better vnto his paſſyon contynually, both for the remyſſyon of theyr ſynnes, &amp; for the receyuyng of his heauenly grace and goodnes alſo, to amende them agayne. Yea and that theſe ſygnes myght the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter for our capacytie, do thys thing, he ordeyned theym of ſuche of hys good creatures as myght, by theyr naturall proprytyes whiche he had geuen vnto theim to do ſeruyce vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:11356:18"/> oure bodies, partely declare what goodneſſe he woulde nowe ſhewe by them alſo, vnto oure ſoules. As fyrſte,<note place="margin">Rom. v.</note> forbycauſe the nature of man was by deriuation holy defiled, and brought with it ſuch a vycyous and corrupt infection as coulde not lye ſtyll, but continually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uoke vs to all kynde of ſyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>mall inſtinction, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efore hys good crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or that it had thys naturall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rytte with it to waſhe awaye the fylth of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die when it was powred on) to certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye vs that our ſoules were inward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly waſhed frome the fylth of ſynne, and we admitted into his flocke, tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe the merytes of hys paſſyon, when this water was powred vpon vs after his commaundement in to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And further leſte man ſhoulde thynke the ſtrengthe and vertue of
<pb facs="tcp:11356:19"/> thys waſſhyng away of the fylth of our ſoules, geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs at our baptime, myght yet decaye and not be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for vs at all tymes, yf by fraylty we fell vnto ſynne agayne afterwar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, and ſo fell alſo from the fayth &amp; truſt in the fauour of God whyche we had ones conceyued by our bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme, he ordeyned the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge and famyliar declaryng of hys comfortable paſſion and louing death, (bycauſe the familiar talking which one of vs hath wyth an other doth often times co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort ſuch greatly as are in any aduerſitie or heuines) to certifye vs, that he wolde renewe vs vnto the ſame fauour of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne whych we had ones co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyued at the fyrſt, and take awaye our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes by the meanes of hys paſſion, when ſo euer hys paſſion and death was preached and declared vnto vs after hys commaundement, in token of the ſame.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11356:19"/>
            <p>And thyrdly, to thintent we ſhuld doute nothyng of thys our renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng vnto the grace and fauoure of God agayne, and vnto the clene ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng away of our ſynnes after our fall, when we were called to the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng vnto it by the preachyng and famyliar declaryng of his meke paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion and louyng death, for that the myniſtration therof was a thynge done in commune and to a great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre at ones, wherof ſome of them myght paraduenture feare whether the wordes of it did ſpecially belong vnto them or no: he dyd ordeyne his good creatures bread and wyne (by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe they had thys natural proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wyth them of noryſſhyng the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye) to certifye vs by the gyuynge of a ſygne of the ſame vnto euerye manne, as it were into hys owne hande, that hys bodye breakynge and bloude ſhedynge ſhoulde at all tymes nouryſſhe and feade
<pb facs="tcp:11356:20"/> our ſoules from al ſynne, death, and the deuell, when ſo euer this breade and wyne was myniſtred vnto vs after hys commaundement in token of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Theſe .iii. ſygnes and tokens ſpecyally, dyd our moſte louyng ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour inſtitute and ordeyne for our weake neceſſitie, to cauſe vs at all ſuche tymes as he ſhoulde preſente or ſende the ſame vnto vs, to truſte ſo muche the more aſſuredly to hys paſſion and death, both for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon of our ſynnes, and for the recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge of hys plentyfull grace and goodneſſe alſo, to amende theym a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne.</p>
            <p>And now that theſe ſygnes and tokens maye certyfye and cauſe vs the more aſſuredlye to beleue in the remyſſyon of all oure ſynnes fyrſte, when ſo euer any of theym is mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred vnto vs, ſhal eaſely be percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. For inaſmuche as they be of
<pb facs="tcp:11356:20"/> Chriſtes owne inſtitutyng, and that to put vs continuallye in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the worthy acceptyng of hys paſſyon, ſo are they playne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſes whiche do ſhewe and moſte certeynly witneſſe hys paſſyon to pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifie ſo the wrath of God for our ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes that it doeth continuallye bothe purchaſe vs the remyſſyon of al our ſynnes, and alſo offer and preſente vnto vs freely the grace and good wyll of God by theſe ſygnes and to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kens to helpe vs to beleue ſurely in the ſame, when ſo euer any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is miniſtred vnto vs after his commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement. For to what purpoſe els, ſhoulde he haue ordeyned ſuch ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and tokens to put vs contynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in remembraunce of the worthy acceptyng of his paſſyon, ſeynge we are ſo farre vnable to geue fayth to the ſame for the remiſſion of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (how playnly ſo euer it be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto vs) that we can not thinke
<pb facs="tcp:11356:21"/> one good thought of our ſelues, yea ſo farre vnlyke are we to haue that godly gyft fayth of our ſelues,<note place="margin">ii. co. iii.</note> that all the powers of oure bodye are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the whole lawes of God, yf the grace and good wyll of God,<note place="margin">Ro. vii.</note> were not of promyſe thorow the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of Chriſtes paſſyon, freely pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſented with theſe ſignes, to helpe vs vnto fayth, when they be offered vn vs? but ſurely as theſe ſygnes and tokens are of Chriſtes owne inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng, and that to put vs continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in remembraunce of hys paſſyon and death ſuffred for our ſynnes, ſo are they playne promyſes whiche do ſhewe and wytneſſe hys paſſion and death to offer and preſent vnto vs frely by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">God ope<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth the dore of fayth. Act. xiiii</note> the grace and good wyl of God for to open oure hertes, to geue fayth vnto theim, when ſo euer they are miniſtred vnto vs after his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement. And therfore as the grace &amp; good wyll of God whych is
<pb facs="tcp:11356:21"/> frely preſented and applyed by theſe ſignes for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merites of Chriſtes paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, can eaſely at al tymes open our hertes to geue credence vnto al ſuch thynges as they do ſhewe and wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: ſo may it well be ſayd therfore that they do certifye &amp; cauſe vs the more aſſuredly to beleue in Chriſtes death for the remiſſion of our ſinnes fyrſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo euer any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred vnto vs according to his inſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tution. And ſo forbycauſe they do thus, frely offre &amp; preſent vnto al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> indifferently the grace &amp; good wyll of God thorow the merites of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes paſſion, at al ſuch tymes as they be miniſtred according to theyr inſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therfore doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture plain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſaye:<note place="margin">Titu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iii Acte. ii. and .xxii Mathe. xviii. i. Cor. xi.</note> baptiſme is the bath of rege<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; waſſheth away our ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell doth forgeue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr ſynne: &amp; the bread &amp; wine in the holy ſouper co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municateth vnto vs the holy and bloude of Chriſte:
<pb facs="tcp:11356:22"/> though in dede they do no more in it at the firſte, but healpe vs the more ſuerly to beleue that our ſynnes are frely waſſhed awaye and forgeuen vs by the body and blode of Chriſte in ſufferyng deathe for vs here: by ſhewynge vs that the effecte of the ſame paſſyon and death, doeth, at al ſuche tymes as they are myniſtred vnto vs, offre and preſent vnto vs the grace and good wyll of God fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to helpe vs to beleue ſurely in the ſame.</p>
            <p>Well thus ye ſee that theſe ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and tokens do of promeſſe (as farre forth yet as they be moued of their promyſer) offer and preſent vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs frely the grace and good wyll of God, for the merites of Chriſtes paſſyon, that they myghte cauſe vs the better to beleue in the remyſſyon of our ſynnes fyrſte, when ſo euer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is miniſtred vnto vs, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge to their inſtitution, and that
<pb facs="tcp:11356:22"/> bycauſe they be of Chriſtes own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtytutyng, for the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And further that they maye wel certyfye and cauſe vs the better to beleue that we ſhall receyue by them alſo, the verye ſame mekeneſſe, loue, and charite, whiche Chriſte offered vp for vs vpon the croſſe, maye in lykewyſe be eaſely perceyued. For in that Chriſt dyd not geue hys bleſſed body to be broken and his precious blod to be ſhedde, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole effecte, vertue, and ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof, might be no more but to obteyne vs freely the grace and good wyll of God for to healpe vs vnto fayth in the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon of our ſynnes, and ſo to let vs fall by and by vnto ſynne agayne, but that it myght be all our holines and ryghteouſneſſe alſo: ſo maye we well beleue that ſeyng the grace and good wyll of god is thorow the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytes of Chriſtes paſſion, freely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented wyth theſe ſignes for to helpe
<pb facs="tcp:11356:23"/> vs vnto a ſure fayth and confidence in the remiſſion of all oure ſynnes fyrſt, that it is there preſent to apply and geue vs by them alſo, al the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe and ryghteouſneſſe of hys death and body, that is to ſaye, both the verye ſame mekeneſſe, loue, and charitie, that was in hys natural bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye when he ſuffered death for vs here, and as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame is alſo of effecte, ſtrength and vertue in hym ſyttyng at the ryghte hande of God for vs nowe: for to make vs lyke vnto hys owne ymage in expreſſyng of theſe hys heauenly vertues or ſpirituall ſubſtaunce vnto other. For howe myghte he elles be called oure hole ryghteouſneſſe and holyneſſe in this worlde alſo, yf he ſhulde not ſet oure fayth in ſuche poſſeſſion of theſe his vertues, beynge the ſubſtaunce of hys verye bodye and heauenly lyfe, as myght bothe kepe vs frome the
<pb facs="tcp:11356:23"/> fallyng vnto ſynne agayne (ſo long as we wyll applye oure lyues vnto them) and alſo cauſe vs to hope ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely to haue the ful vſe of them in an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other worlde? But ſurely ſeynge the effecte ſtrength, and vertue of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bodye is not onely the meanes wherby we come vnto a ſure faythe and truſte in the remiſſion of al our ſynnes, fyrſt by hys ſufferyng death for vs here, but is alſo the verye ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuouſe meanes wherby we come vnto all other holyneſſe and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, by hys ſyttyng at the right hande of God for vs now, we maye well thynke that as he frely preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and geueth vs fyrſt by theſe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes the grace &amp; good wyll of God for to helpe vs the better vnto a ſure fayth in the remiſſion of all our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that the ſame grace &amp; good wyl of God ſhall helpe vs by them alſo, vnto all the other ſtrength and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of hys bodye and heauenly lyfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11356:24"/>
            <p>And ſo forbycauſe they do freely thus preſent vnto vs the grace and good wyll of God for to helpe vs to both theſe thynges, thorow the effect of Chriſtes body, as it was both in ſufferyng death for vs here and as it is in ſyttynge at the ryghte hande of God for vs nowe alſo, when ſo euer they be miniſtred accordyng to theyr inſtytucyon, therefore dyd ſayncte Paule ſpeakynge of holye baptyſme,<note place="margin">Ro. vi.</note> ſaye alſo: we are buryed wyth hym by baptyſme, for to dye: that lykewiſe as Chriſte was reyſed vp frome death by the glorye of hys heauenly father, ſo we alſo ſhoulde walke in a newe lyfe. By the whiche wordes doubtleſſe he meaned not that baptiſme was a ſygne that cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed vs the better to beleue oure ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes paſte onely to be buried in the death of Chriſte, in that it dyd wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the grace of God to be frely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto vs for to helpe vs to do
<pb facs="tcp:11356:24"/> the ſame: but that we were endued by it alſo, wyth the ſame lyfe that Chriſte dyd ryſe agayne in, that is to ſaye, with the ſame mekeneſſe, loue, and charite that was in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye when he dyd ryſe agayne: for to burye in vs (yf we woulde applye our lyues therafter) thoſe remanen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of ſynne alſo, whiche dyd yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde in vs after faythe, and whyche myghte elles cauſe vs to fall vnto ſynne agayne afterwarde.</p>
            <p>And he ſpeakyng alſo of the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the lorde,<note place="margin">i. cor. xi.</note> called it the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or partakyng of the body and blode of Chriſt. By the whiche ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng he meaned not that this breade and wyne whyche was vſed in the holy ſouper, was a ſigne that might cauſe vs the better to beleue in the bodye and blode of Chriſte for the remyſſyon of oure ſynnes paſte on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, in that it dyd preſente vnto vs freely, the grace of God to helpe vs
<pb facs="tcp:11356:25"/> to do the ſame, but that they dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate vnto vs alſo the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of his nature, as his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall mekeneſſe, loue, and charyte, for to nouryſhe our bodyes to an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly lyfe, yf we woulde applye our ſelues vnto them.</p>
            <p>Yea and this was his meaning alſo when he called the preaching of the goſpell: the power of god to all them beleuynge in it.<note place="margin">Rom. i.</note> For it geueth forth ſuch a ſtrengthe and power of goddes grace, thorow the merites of Chriſtes paſſion, as dothe not onely delyuer vs from ſynnes paſt, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentyng of our faythe vnto vs to helpe vs to beleue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſurely: but alſo it delyuereth vs from thoſe ſynnes that might come vpon vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne afterwarde, yf we wyll dyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently geue ouer our ſelfes to it and to the reſt of hys lawes.</p>
            <p>Well by theſe thinges nowe a foreſayde, it is ſumwhat manifeſt,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:25"/> what the worde and ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes are, and what thinges god geueth vs by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: to wete, theſe .ii. thinges ſpecialli Firſt he geueth vs our fayth the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye, he cauſeth vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better to beleue hys paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; death to be oures at all tymes, in that he ſheweth &amp; witneſſeth by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as by to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kens of his owne inſtituting for the ſame purpoſe, that his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuallye of ſo muche ſtrength and vertue for vs, that it doth frely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre &amp; preſent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace &amp; good wyll of God vnto vs by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for to helpe vs to beleue ſuerly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al our ſinnes fyrſt, when ſo euer any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is miniſtred vnto vs after his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, ſeyng that Chriſte dyed not to helpe vs vnto fayth onely in this worlde, but to geue vs a part of his heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly life alſo for to cauſe vs the better to hope after a more full vſe of it here afterwarde, as he dyd nowe geue
<pb facs="tcp:11356:26"/> vs an earneſt therof, ſo dothe he geue vs by theſe ſygnes alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſubſtaunce of his body and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly lyfe, for to helpe vs to reforme oure lyues accordynge to the ſame.</p>
            <p>Wherfore I may well conclude vpon this ſacrament of breade and wyne (as I maye nowe from hence forth let the other .ii. paſſe) that it is a ſygne, &amp; toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherby our ſauiour Chriſt doth miniſter and geue both theſe thinges in ſpeakyng this ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifycation vnto vs thus by it: as this breade and wyne is at my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement geuen vnto you to be eaten and dronken into your bodies as your owne fode, ſo is my death &amp; reſurreccion your owne fode in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentinge vnto you, at al ſuche times as this ſygne ſhall be offred vnto you, the grace and good wyll of god frely, for to make you beleue ſuerly in my deth and reſurrection both for the remyſſion of your ſynnes, and
<pb facs="tcp:11356:26"/> for the receyuyng of all the ſtrength and vertue of my heauenly life alſo, for to helpe you frome fallyng vnto ſynne againe hereafterward, ſo farre forth as you wyll applye your dyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence therunto, and ſuffer my ſpirite to rule you in it. And therfore ſeyng that thorow this ſignification there is of promiſe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpiritually both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue &amp; ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy in ſufferyng death for vs here, &amp; alſo the effect &amp; ſpiritual ſubſtaunce of his body beyng now in heauen, ſo myght Chriſt well ſay of the breade whiche he vſed at his holy ſouper:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>This is my body whiche ſhall be geuen for you:</hi>
            </q>
            <p>And of the cup in lykewyſe myght he well ſaye:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Thys cuppe is the newe teſtament in my blod whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhall be ſhedde for you
<pb facs="tcp:11356:27"/> and for many vnto the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſion of ſynnes.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>And fynally, foraſmuch as theſe ſygnes and tokens do thus preuent vs with the grace and good will of god, only for the merites of Chriſtes paſſion to helpe vs to a ſure faythe in the remiſſion of our ſynnes, and to all the ſtrengthe and vertue of Chriſtes body and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly life alſo, that we might amende our liues af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde and ſerue hym in all holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe, therfore are theſe ſygnes and tokens (for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter declaracion of their offyce) called ſacramentes, that is to ſaye godlye ceremonies, or exerciſes ordeyned of god, for to ſacrat and make vs holy euen with Chriſtes owne holyneſſe and goodnes.</p>
            <p>Theſe thinges now beyng had in remembraunce, do of them ſelues, in a manner, declare what honoure
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="4 pages">
                  <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:11356:27"/> dynaunce, this is to be iudged of all Chriſten men. That as we can not be ſure that it is the ſacramente of Chriſte, or of his bodye and blood, but when it doeth the office that he hath appoynted vnto it, in miny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring forth of his mynde and ſygni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, ſo ought we not to ſaye that we can conceyue as moche comforte and faith by the vſynge of it anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe, than euen after his owne inſtitution &amp; ordynance. And againe, ſeynge that Chriſte hathe ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this ſacrament to be oftentimes preſented vnto vs, as well as he woulde haue vs oftentymes called vpon for the dylygente hearynge of his holy goſpell, and for the vſyng of his holy commaundementes, as faſt, prayer &amp; almoſe dedes, ſo oughte this to be iudged alſo of all chriſten men: that as he woulde neuer haue done this, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> weaknes of oure fayth had not ſo required it, ſo oughte
<pb facs="tcp:11356:28"/> we to obeye his commaundement in makynge of oure fayth ſure that we be ledde and poſſeſſed ſtyll of his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſpirite within, by the receiuyng of this ſacrament when ſo euer we can conueniently come vnto the ſame. Wherefore this is the ſeconde ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour dew vnto this ſacrament, that we, by the receyuynge of it after the ſame maner &amp; ordre that he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it to be a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto vs, do ſtrengthen our fayth by it bothe for the remiſſion of our ſynnes, &amp; for the receyuyng of his heauenly body &amp; life alſo, to amende them agayne.</p>
            <p>The thyrde honour is, that ſeyng god doth of his mere goodnes geue vnto vs ſuch giftes in this his holy ſacra. as the very effecte &amp; ſpirituall ſubſtaunce of his owne precious bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy &amp; bloode, as it was both in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng deth for vs here, &amp; as it is now makynge interceſſion for vs at the ryghte hande of God, ſo is it oure
<pb facs="tcp:11356:28"/> bound dewtie agayne to applye our hole lyues to the vtterynge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowynge of theſe ſame hys gyftes ſo after we haue receyued them that hys moſte holy wyll therby, myght the better bothe in our ſelues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be fulfylled, and his kingdome enlarged. And ſpecially ſeyng he doth ſo louyngly, yea moſte charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ioyne vs together into his owne body, as fleſhe of hys fleſhe &amp; bone of hys bones, by makyng vs parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the effect and ſubſtaunce of hym ſelfe, thorow the faythful recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng together of thys hys myſtical breade, that is to ſaye, thorow the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyuing of his godly ſpirite, mynde, and wyl in it, ſo ought we agayne to be charitable &amp; louyng one to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; one to fede &amp; noryſhe another with al our wordes &amp; dedes, that we myght growe vp &amp; walke forth toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther in the ſtrength of the ſame meat vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te of Oreb, the felicite of
<pb facs="tcp:11356:29"/> heauen. Well, theſe .iii. kyndes of honoure then are ſpecially due vnto this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or rather to the grace of god preſent in it, at all ſuch times as it ſhal be preſented vnto vs after Chriſtes ordinaunce.</p>
            <p>And nowe that theſe .iii. kyndes of honouring this ſacramente, are ſo ſpecially due vnto it whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred accordynge to Chriſtes ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce, that without the effecte of them all .iii. together, it can be had in no reuerence nor honour of vs, may wel be perceyued by the honour that they of the olde tyme, ſhoulde haue geuen to their ſacrifices, which were vnto them ſacramentes. Whom the lorde dyd greatly reproue as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt abuſers and deſpiſers of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, bicauſe they did leaue vndone the honoure and reuerence whiche he had ſpecyally appointed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do vnto hym in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by ſaying thus vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorowe his holy pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet
<pb facs="tcp:11356:29"/> Ieremy.<note place="margin">Iere. vii</note> Thus ſaieth the lorde of hoſtes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God of Iſrael: put your burned offerynges, &amp; other offeryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges together, and eate vp the fleſhe. For I haue not, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I brought your fathers out of Egipte, ſpoken vnto them, nor geuen them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement of burned offrynges and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offrynges. But thys I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them, ſayeng: herken &amp; obeye my voyce: and I ſhal be your God, and you ſhalbe my people. Walke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all the wayes that I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded you that ye may proſper. But they wold not heare me, nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyne theyr eares vnto me. Beholde, whiles the Iewes dyd offre vp theyr ſacrifices, whych were ſuch holy cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monies as God had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded him ſelf to be offred vnto him, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce had before for theyr former ſinnes, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the ſtrengthening a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of their faith in chriſt for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me, not geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g eare to this his minde
<pb facs="tcp:11356:30"/> and meanyng in them, for the which they were chiefly ordeyned, he ſayde vnto them: they ſhulde but put their offeringes together, and eate vp the fleſhe of them them ſelues, for he had geuen them no commaundement of them. As to wete, that they ſhuld of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre them ſo vnto hym, in puttyng theyr hole truſte of honouryng hym or of doyng hym ſeruice, in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward doyng of them, without the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyuing of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, faith, &amp; purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe of amendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fre preſenting of his grace &amp; good wil in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before And in lyke wyſe, when the Iewes wolde lyue out of charitie with their neyghbours, or requyt euel for euel, without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion taking in al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, and thynke yet to pleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde with the outwarde doyng of ſuch ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>remonies &amp; ſacrifices as he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, the lord ſayd thus vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the prophet Amos:<note place="margin">Amos. v</note> I wyll haue mercymeat and no ſacrifice. By the
<pb facs="tcp:11356:30"/> whych ſayeng he dyd not yet forbid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem to do that thynge with al reue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence, which he had ones co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut he wylled them not to do it in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruſte to honour or pleaſe hym any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hynge therby, wythout they had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eyued before, ſuch a fayth and truſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the fre remiſſion of theyr ſynnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>horow Chriſt, by the inſtitutyng of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe ſacrifices, as had made them of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynde to folowe and obey all hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommaundementes, but ſpecially in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hewing of mercy vnto al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, like as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e had ſhewed it frely vnto theym.</p>
            <p>Thorow Eſaye the prophete the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orde ſayd alſo that ſuch offerynges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſacrifices as he had yet hyghly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded hym ſelfe to be offered,<note place="margin">Eſay. i.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere abhomination vnto hym, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he coulde not ones abyde them. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ote here, good reader. thys wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſeth God of the ſeruice, whyche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e people woulde yet ſeme to do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto hym ſelfe and not to anye
<pb facs="tcp:11356:31"/> ſtraunge Goddes, and that in ſuche thynges as were not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to be done by man, but, as touchynge to the doyng of theym in forme and maner outwardly as they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, by God hym ſelfe. Onely bicauſe they would nedes do him ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyce in theym, withoute the concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge before of ſuche a faythe and truſte in the free remyſſyon of theyr ſynnes by the merites of Chriſte, as had brought theym in mynde bothe to repent them of their ſynnes, and alſo to amende theyr lyues. Nowe if the vſyng of the ſacramentes were thus abhominable to him ones, that he coulde not abyde the ſyght of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when they had not their true honour gyuen vnto them, howe dwely ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they wer obſerued and honored outwardely: what wyll he ſay then i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we do now vſe his holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes whiche be of no leſſe ſtrength &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue than were theyrs in olde tym
<pb facs="tcp:11356:31"/> but rather of more, wythout theſe iii. thynges be ſurely grounded in oure myndes before? wherefore it is manyfeſt that neyther oure golde nor other goodes, neyther our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng downe nor knelynge before them, neyther yet oure often vſynge of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> outwardely, can be any thing to the honouryng of the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, or to the grace of God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in theym, excepte we do fyrſte wyth harty repentaunce cal to mind the greate nede that we haue of the fre grace preſented in them thorowe Chriſte, for oure dayly ſynnes, and excepte we do then ſtrengthen oure faith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to his ordynance, and ſo geue ouer our ſelues holly to all other his lawes. And althoughe theſe .iii. thinges now a fore ſayd, be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpecial kindes of honouryng this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodye &amp; blod of Chriſt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is miniſtred vnto vs, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo due vnto it
<pb facs="tcp:11356:32"/> that with out the effecte of them all iii. together it can not be honoured or had in any reuerence of vs (lyke as I haue ſayd:) yet ſeyng the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mekeneſſe of oure penytent and faythfull hertes, dothe alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre that both all our goodes and membres ſhoulde ſerue to the better expreſſyng of the ſame, when ſoeuer we wyll ſhew it forth ether in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuyng of this ſacrament, or in the doynge of any other godly exercyſe: ſo dothe it require theſe tokens or kyndes of honouring this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be preſente alſo when we wyll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it. Firſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we prouide a place both honeſt, comly, and ſeueral from all other buſynes, for the commune miniſtracion of this holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, with inſtrumentes right ſemyng for ſame. And ſecondely, that we applye al the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of our bodyes to ſerue to the humble mekeneſſe of our pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytent and faythfull hertes, at the
<pb facs="tcp:11356:32"/> reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t receyuing of this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: as to wete, that we receyue it with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> humble vncoueryng of our heades, with the bowyng of oure bodyes or knelyng downe, &amp; with the lawdyng and prayſynge of his goodnes in it with our tounges alſo. Theſe be to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trew honouring of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament alſo, as far forth as they do aſſure both our ſelues and other of our vnfeynedneſſe and trewe recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of it. For as that mynde is trewly penytente, whiche cauſeth all the bodye to ſhewe mekeneſſe, as the harte to ſighe for ſorow, the handes to be lyfted vp or the knees to be bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed down for feare, &amp; the tounge to breake forth in cryeng for mercy: ſo are theſe ſure tokens of the trew ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouryng of god alſo, whan the hart doth ſhewe them forth, whether they be done at the receyuyng of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament or at any other godly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe. And forbycauſe they do moſte
<pb facs="tcp:11356:33"/> certeynly thus, aſſure both our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and other of our vnfeyned hert and pure mynde, therefore are theſe tokens taken in the ſcripture for the honouryng of God it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Mathe. iiii.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But as no man can expreſſe theſe outwarde tokens a ryghte, whyche hath not partly receyued before, tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe the ſygnification or meanyng of Chriſte in this his holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the other .iii. ſpecyall tokens, that is to ſaye, whyche hathe not partelye wyth an humble and penytent herte before, conſydered ſo farre forth the goodneſſe of Chriſte in the ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge and preſentynge of thys ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente for to ſhewe hys death to apperteyne vnto vs at all ſuche ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes as it is miniſtred, that he both truſteth ſo muche the more aſſuredly in it, for the remyſſyon of hys ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and fully purpoſeth alſo to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende hys lyfe thorow the aſſyſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſame grace &amp; goodnes whych
<pb facs="tcp:11356:33"/> he ſhall then preſently receyue by it: ſo are theſe outwarde tokens not to be taken as ſygnes of the true hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng of Chriſte in this ſacramente, but when the other .iii. are from with in ioyned with theym.</p>
            <p>The whiche .iii. inwarde tokens can not be ioyned with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſygnes a ryghte, but in and at the receyuyng of this ſacramente onely (for then onely doeth thys ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament geue vs a ſure fayth in the death of Chriſt, out of the which the inwarde repentaunce of the mynd &amp; the purpoſe to amende with al other tokens of humilite doth ſpring) ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore are theſe outward tokens plain ydolatry, yf they be at any other ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me expreſſed or done to thys ſacra. but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is miniſtred according to Chriſtes ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Wherfore thus I wyll conclude vpon theſe latter kind of toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we do honour this ſacra. Yf we can firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue by
<pb facs="tcp:11356:34"/> the preſentyng of it vnto vs, a harty repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for our ſynnes paſt, and then a ſure faith in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Chriſt for the remiſſion of the ſame againe, with a good purpoſe to amende, we do honoure the grace of god and the preſence of Chriſt in this ſacrament (for the breade and wyne haue no power of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to geue vs ſuche thinges) thoughe we do kneele or bowe downe oure bodyes to it alſo, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we do receyue it. But yf we can not firſt honoure it thus, then do we honoure the creatures of breade and wyne for them ſelues, yf we do ether bowe down or lyft vp our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to them, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myttyng therwith playne ydolatrye. And therfore as thyne owne hart muſt be thy guide in this matter, ſo is it nedefull that thou ſaye thus with Dauid, in goyng to receyue this holy ſouper: directe my foteſteppes, o lord, and teache me to do thy wyll. For thou only muſte
<pb facs="tcp:11356:34"/> geue vs before the gift of grace and knowlege, of thy mere goodnes and for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merites of thy ſon Ieſu Chriſt, or els we can not take it vnto vs ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther in this ſacramente nor in anye thynge elles. We humbly beſech the therfore ſo to illuminate our hertes wyth the preſnce of thy holy ſpirite, that we, in receyuyng of thys holye ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, may receyue alſo thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wyll therin: Amen.</p>
            <p>Well, thus muche is ſayde, for thys tyme, concernyng the ryght ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nouryng of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt in this ſacrament, when it is mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred at the holy ſouper. Whereby maye be perceyued that bothe theſe kyndes of honouryng it are requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte, thoughe not of lyke, nor in lyke place. For the inwarde worſhipping of it muſt nedes haue the firſt place, and is ſo ſpecyall, that with out the tokens therof, thys ſacramente can be had in no kind of reuerence: wher
<pb facs="tcp:11356:35"/> the outwarde tokens are not onely but in the ſeconde place, but are alſo ſubiect to all kyndes of neceſſitie. As to wete, yf our owne neceſſitie or our neighbours, or elles that the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me and place wyll not conueniently permyt vs to lyft vp our handes, or to kneele downe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhal receiue it, they are not ſo greatly to be paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on, nor to be taryed for, neceſſitie holdeth vs excuſed. But the inward worſhippyng of it wyth ſure fayth in the death of Chriſte, wherout re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce and amendement of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng doth enſue, is ſo dew vnto it, that no neceſſitie can excuſe it. And yet the Pope had brought thys ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to ſuche an vſe, that it was continually reſerued and dayly ſette forth before the people in the maſſe, wythout any mencion makyng of the inwarde worſhippyng of it, but onely that it myght be outwardlye worſhypped wyth the lyftyng vp of
<pb facs="tcp:11356:35"/> handes and bowyng of knees, wyth candels, torches and ſuche lyke: the ſtyrryng vp of repentaunce, fayth, &amp; amendeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of lyuyng beyng left to the blynde conſcience of man, whych is yet dull ynough when it is moſte ſharpely pricked forward vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yea and to proue this abuſyng of it to be yet the cauſe of muche good de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uotion amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the people, he brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght forth not onely goodly argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes and reaſons, (as they appeared outwardly) but alſo certayne places and enſamples of the ſcripture for the ſame. And ſo thus he ſayd for to proue that we ſhoulde continuallye honoure thys ſacrament wyth han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and knees, whether we dyd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly worſhyppe it or no.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ In thys ſacrament there is preſente the bodye and bloude of Chriſte: and therfore oughte we to wourſhyppe it wyth handes and
<pb facs="tcp:11356:36"/> knees whether we do ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our fayth by the corporall receyuynge of it, or no.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwere.</label> Chriſte ſayth that he and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil be ſo preſent with them that kepe hys commaundementes,<note place="margin">Iohn .xiiii.</note> that they wyll both come and dwell with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And Saint Paul ſaith alſo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde Chriſt dwelleth thorow faith in the hertes of the elected.<note place="margin">Eph. iii.</note> And yet it doth not folow of this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld fall downe vpon our knees before godly and deuout people, as though we could receyue Chriſt preſently, by the honouringe of him ſo, in theym. The lorde in dede geueth effectually hys very body and blode in this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament when it is miniſtred accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to hys ordynaunce, and yet we can not receyue it with the worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pynge of it wyth handes and knees onely. But ſpecyally we muſte fyrſt wourſhyppe it wyth the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:11356:36"/> and knees of our fayth, lyke as we do onely receyue and fele him pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſente there with the mouthe of oure fayth. The preſence of Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and blode in this ſacramente, is an heauenly worke, that is to ſaye, it is wrought into vs by the ſpryte of God onely and thorow the decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of the goodnes and merytes of Chriſtes paſſyon, and is no work of thys worlde, that he is preſent to be geuen vs there. And therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we wyll ether receyue or worſhyppe it there,<note place="margin">By the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t we muſte ſyng ſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſum cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>da.</note> we muſte fyrſte ſynge thus with the church: <hi>Surſum corda, et non huc corda.</hi> That is to ſaye, we muſte fyrſt lyfte vp oure hertes aboue al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be felt or ſene in it, &amp; thorow faith lay hand vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodnes of Chriſt, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering this ſacra. to be a plain promyſe which doth moſte certeynly witnes &amp; ſhew his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cified ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wrath of God for our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinualli purchaſe vs
<pb facs="tcp:11356:37"/> both the remiſſion of them al, &amp; frely offre and preſent vnto vs alſo the grace and good wyll of god no leſſe for to helpe vs to beleue ſurely in it than to amende the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe, when ſo euer it is myniſtred vnto vs. The whiche faith as no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can haue that entendeth not to receyue it when ſo euer it is miniſtred vnto hym, euen ſo can there no man worſhyppe this ſacrament a ryght with handes and knees that dothe not receyue it alſo.</p>
               <p>Wherefore although trew faith bryngeth well to paſſe,<note place="margin">What outward worſhyp true faith bringeth forth.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we, by this moſt holy miniſtracion, do oftenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes fal downe vpon out knees and lyft vp oure handes, ether when we heare theſe moſt holſome wordes of the lorde: take, eate, this is my body whiche ſhall be geuen for you: take, drynke ye all out of this: this cuppe is the new teſtamente in my bloude &amp; cetera: or when we do receyue the
<pb facs="tcp:11356:37"/> moſte comfortable meat and drinke at the miniſtration of the ſacrament in the holy ſouper: yet that we ſhuld therfore take it for an acceptable ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nourynge or worſhippyng of oure Lorde Chriſt, to fal downe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our knees before this ſacrament eyther when it is ſhewed, hanged vp, or borne about, or to do it any kynde of reuerence when it is lyfted vp, &amp; yet not to receyue it accordyng to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ordynaunce, that doutleſſe can not only be gathered out of no word of God, but is alſo playne agaynſte the ſame, where it ſayeth: take eate. &amp;c. take and drynke. For what we muſte forthwyth as it is myniſtred vnto vs, eate and drynke corporally to the ſtrengthenyng of oure fayth, and to the ſtyrryng vp of all godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in vs, that maye we not thynke to receyue by the ſeyng of it when it is lyfted vp or caryed aboute.
<pb facs="tcp:11356:38"/> wherfore it can not be the trewe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouryng of Chriſt in this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but rather a deſpyſyng of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to go aboute to amende and chaunge his ordynaunce in it after our blynde reaſon, in ſaying we wyl honoure him in it, when we wyll not receyue it.</p>
               <p>And therfore to knele down before the ſacrament lyftyng vp handes &amp; eyes towardes it ether when it is in miniſtrynge or otherwyſe ſhewed, of the whiche kynde of honoringe it ether Chriſte nor his apoſtles hath any thing taught, and yet not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it according to his ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, a thing whiche the lorde commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be done with all dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, can be nothing elles than a vayne wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of him in it with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of man, as I ſhall plainly proue by this argument.</p>
               <p>It is all a vayne worſhyppinge of Chriſt in this his holy ſacrament,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:38"/> when we wyll not humbly and with all faythfull obedyence receyue the gyft and benefyte whiche he offereth vs by the myniſtracion of theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in it: take eate, take, and drinke. But they do not worſhyppe Chriſte a right with the humble receyuinge of the benefyte whiche he preſenteth vnto them by the myniſtracion of theſe wordes that wyl not take, eate, and drynke this ſacrament after his ordynaunce, when he commaundeth them to do it. And therefore all the worſhypping of Chriſt in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without the humble and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full receyuing of it alſo after his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunce, is but a vayne worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of him in it, and the doctrine of man.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, to worſhip Chriſt in the ſacramente with handes and knees, and yet not to receyue it after his ordinaunce, what other thynge maye it ſhewe elles, than y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we wyll
<pb facs="tcp:11356:39"/> encloſe Chriſt our lorde in the bread comprehenſyblye, byndynge hym ſo vnto it, and bring him therwith into an earthely liuing and being again?<note place="margin">To wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe Chriſte a ryght in thys ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament what it is.</note> where we ſhoulde yet lift vp our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues by and by as it is preſented, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vyſyble ſygne to the inuyſyblye grace whiche it dothe ſygnifye, and from the earthely miniſtracion of it, to the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly goodnes of hym that ordeyned it to be miniſtred, and ſo worſhyp in it Chriſte oure lorde in ſpirite and truth, that is to ſay, moſt inwardely and hartely remembryng then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodnes of our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt, whiche woulde ſhewe vs by it that his paſſion had ſo pacyfyed the wrathe of god, for oure ſynnes, that it dyd continually purchaſe vs the remyſſion of them all, and frely offre and preſente vnto vs therfore by this ſacramente the grace and good wyll of god, for to helpe vs both to beleue ſurely in it, &amp; alſo to
<pb facs="tcp:11356:39"/> amende our liues again. The which faith (as I haue ſaid) as no can haue truly, which is not by &amp; by readye to receyue after Chriſtes ordynaunce, hys holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reuerence bothe of bodye and mynde, as ſoone as it is preſented vnto hym, ſo is thys onely the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppynge of God in ſpirite and trueth in or by this holy ſacrament: fyrſte to conceyue ſuche a faythe in the goodnes of Chriſt by it, as maye cauſe vs ſurely to truſte both to the remiſſion of our ſinnes &amp; to the recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge of ſo moche grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe alſo by the corporall eatynge and drynkynge of it, as maye helpe vs to amende our lyues. And then to geue ouer oure ſelues holly to the lawdynge and prayſynge of hys name, and to the folowynge of hys commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, both in the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble receyuyng of this ſacrament, and in folowynge of hys other lawes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:11356:40"/>
               <p>¶ The ſeconde argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wherwith the pope woulde proue that this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament ſhoulde be reſerued, kepte, and ſhewed to be honoured of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple with handes and knees, though they dyd not receyue it, is this. The Arke of promeſſe, &amp; the Mercye ſeat was continually worſhypped of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the olde tyme, whiche was a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. And therfore (ſayth he) we ought to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyke vnto this ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at all tymes, though we do not receiue it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwere.</label> God dyd ordeyne this Arke and Mercie ſeate for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the olde time to put them continuallye in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce that he would ſuerly be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent amongeſt them, to fulfyll all the promeſſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had made vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The which Arke and Mercye ſeate bycauſe it ſhoulde continuallye put
<pb facs="tcp:11356:40"/> theym in remembraunce of the ſure fulfyllynge of hys promyſſes, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was it bothe reſerued contynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and alſo had in all reuerence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the people when they wold receyue thys remembraunce at it. But the breade and wyne hathe not the lorde ordeined to be reſerued con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynuallye, or to be lyfted vp for a ſhewe, but geuen it to be eaten and dronken at an holy ſouper with this ſygnifycatyon: as I do geue you thys breade and wyne to be eaten &amp; dronken into youre bodyes as your owne foode, ſo ſhall my bodye and blode noryſhe and fede your ſoules wyth the grace &amp; good wyl of God, for to helpe you both to beleue ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in it for the remiſſion of your ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and alſo to amende the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. And therfore as thys ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doth not miniſtre thys ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, nether by the reſeruyng of it, nor by the ſhewyng of it after any
<pb facs="tcp:11356:41"/> ſuche meanes, as the Arke dyd, but onely when it is geuen vs to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and dronken wyth thys remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, ſo is it then onely to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, when it is ſo receyued in the holy ſouper. But before I ſpeake any further of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trewe worſhypping of thys ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I wyll fyrſt ſhewe howe the primatiue churche vſed to worſhyp it.</p>
               <p>¶ What the fayth and vſe of the primatiue church hath bene of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppyng thys ſacrament.</p>
               <p>That they of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primatiue church haue wyth al reuerence and honour myniſtred, handled, &amp; receyued thys holy ſacrament, of it we fynde wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ynough. But that they haue worſhypped it, kneled downe before it, wyth the lyftyng vp of handes &amp; eyes towardes it, and ſet it forth in golde and ſyluer to be worſhypped, or borne it about in proceſſions, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouryng it wyth candles, torches,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:41"/> ryngyng and ſyngyng, and al other melodye, of that we fynde not onely no wytneſſe, but rather it whereout we may gather clene the contrarye. For we fynde how that certayne by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of Rome dyd vſe to ſende the ſacrament to the gates,<note place="margin">Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, libro v. capi. xxiiii.</note> for to be receyued there of other ſtraunge by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes when they came to vyſite them.<note place="margin">Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us. libro vi. capi. xxxiiii.</note> And we fynde howe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a prieſt dyd geue the ſacrament vnto a boye for to beare home to hys father and to geue it hym there. Alſo we may ſe in the bokes of ſaint Cipriane,<note place="margin">Cipri. in ſermo de Lapſis. Hiero. in Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo. pro li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bris ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Iouia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuliane, and Hierome, how that men were wont in the tyme of thoſe holy fathers, to gyue the ſacrament vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laye people for to beare home with them: and how that the people were wont, after they had ſo receiued it, to laye it vp in theyr chiſtes, or other ſpeciall cuſtodyes,<note place="margin">Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius de ſuo fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro.</note> yea ſome woulde hange it about theyr neckes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it when they lyſt them ſelues.
<pb facs="tcp:11356:42"/> Out of the whych we may well ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that men in thoſe dayes, knewe nothyng of worſhyppyng the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, at the leaſt wayes as it was now worſhypped.</p>
               <p>Honorius tertius, a Pope that lyued and wrytte in the yere of oure Lord. M.CC.xvi. dyd ordeyne that men ſhulde reſerue and kepe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in a place appointed, &amp; that the prieſtes ſhulde oftentymes lerne the people, reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to knele downe when the ſacrament was lyfted vp in the maſſe, or when it was borne vnto the ſycke folke. Beholde, this Pope whiche lyued but .iii. hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and .xxxii. yeares a goo, ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned fyrſte that men ſhoulde reſerue the ſacrament in a place appointed, and that the prieſtes ſhould lerne the people to knele downe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſaw the ſacrament lyfted vp, or borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. Where was than, before thoſe dayes, the goodly pyxes, canapies, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:11356:42"/> lampes, with all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crouchinges and knelynges which we haue vſed? but after the right vſe of the ſacramente whiche god hym ſelfe had commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be kept, was one fallen, it was eaſye ynough for the deuell to brynge in all ſuche ſuperſticious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes, and to cauſe men beleue that they were to the trew honouringe of god and his holy ſacramentes.</p>
               <p>Now is it trewe alſo that in the prymatiue churche there were ſome that did reſerue the bread which thei had remayning ouer the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a ſecrete place tyll the next tyme, &amp; that they had an vſe alſo to ſhewe the breade in the holy ſouper. For as Dioniſius in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iii. chapter <hi>De eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtia</hi> maketh mention, it was the vſe in hys tyme, that the prieſtes ſhould firſt ſet forth vpon the alter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread &amp; chalice couered, and after they had conſecrated, to vncouer them, and bryng them ſo forth into the ſight of
<pb facs="tcp:11356:43"/> the people, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to deale y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breade by and by in peaces, &amp; to geue forth the cuppe in lykemaner. And in the Greke <hi>Liturgia</hi> we rede that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt, a litle before the miniſtringe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note place="margin">The ſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament hath ben <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ge of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, when it was to lifted vp, was neuer v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, tyll of late.</note> dyd lyft vp a lytle the breade, <hi>modicum ſuſtolteus,</hi> like as we vſed to do in our meſſe by and by, after the pater noſter. But that ether the chalyce was at any tyme lyfted vp in thoſe dayes, or el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les that the people fell downe vpon their knees and worſhipped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread beyng ſo lyfted vp, of it we rede no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge, before this Pope Honorius did ordeyne it.</p>
               <p>Wherby we may perceiue, that al though y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhewing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſouper, be wel olde, yet to fal down and worſhip it when it was ſo ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, or to lyft vp handes and eyes to it, and not to receyue it, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, is an abuſe crepte in of late, whiche was vtterly vnknowen
<pb facs="tcp:11356:43"/> to them of the olde tyme. The which kynde of honouringe can as lytle ſtande with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſure of god in this ſacrament, whiche commaundeth vs to take, eate, and drynke it, as could the honouring of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> braſen Serpent with handes &amp; knees, after they had lefte out and forgotten the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of it that god had ordeyned it to preſent and geue vnto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ But thou ſayeſt: when I ſe the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament ether lyfted vp in the maſſe or ſet forth by any other meanes, I can the better call to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance by it, the mercyfull helpe of God whych is vniuerſally preſent. And therfore it is good to ſe the ſacrament at all tymes, and to worſhip it, though we do not receiue it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwere.</label> Fyrſt, for aſmuche as Chriſt hath not ordeyned thys ſacrament to put vs in any godly reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, but by the eatyng and drynkyng of it, at an
<pb facs="tcp:11356:44"/> holy ſouper, ſo ought we not to ſay, that we can the better call to remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance the goodneſſe of God by the ſeyng of it then by the corporall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuyng of it. Nether is it to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſacrament of the bodye and blode of Chriſte, but for one of hys good creatures, except it do put vs in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of his bodye &amp; blode, after hys owne ordinaunce. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to worſhyp a creature wyth handes and knees, is not ynough to ſay, thou wylt, when thou ſeeſt it, cal to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance the vniuerſal helpe of God, but we muſte be ſure alſo, that the creature be ordeyned of god him ſelfe, for to put vs in ſuche a remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance. For a man, and ſpeciallye a godly man, is the excellent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to put vs in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of the goodnes of God, that maye be ether in heauen or in earth. The Sunne, the Moone, &amp; all maner of beaſtes vpon earth are the precious workes
<pb facs="tcp:11356:44"/> of God, and the very ymages of his godly power, whych do manifeſtlye ſhewe forth alſo, his wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and goodnes at al times: lyke as he wytneſſeth hym ſelfe in hys worde. And yet ſo farre is it of that we ſhulde therfore worſhyp any of theſe hys creatures, that it is playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forboden by hys holy worde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ Thou ſayeſt further paraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: why do we then worſhyp oure parentes, prynces and magiſtrates with cappe and knee, ſeyng they are but creatures.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwere.</label> Theſe perſones are appointed of God to teache vs to folowe the lawes of Chriſte, yea and to put vs in remembraunce of the ſame wyth corporall punyſhmentes, yf we do not folowe theyr inſtructions. And therfore we are bounde to be both o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to all theyr good ordinaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and alſo to ſhewe the ſame obedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:11356:45"/> towardes theyr perſones, wyth the humble vncoueryng of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, wyth the knelyng downe vnto them, or ſuche lyke, according to the vſe and maner of euery countre. But God hath not appointed the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of hys body and blode to be worſhypped, for any thyng that we can call to remembraunce by it, but when we do receyue the ſame remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brance by it which he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to geue vnto vs by the corporal eatyng and drynking of it. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſeyng God hath not appointed it to put vs in any remembrance of hys power or goodnes by the ſeyng of it, but hath geuen vs a playne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to receyue it, affirming it to be hys body and blode when he ſpeaketh vnto vs by it, theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: take, eate, thys is my bodye: ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, drynke thys is my blode: by the whych ſaying of Chriſt, as thys vſe can not ſtande that we ſhuld receiue
<pb facs="tcp:11356:45"/> hys bodye and blode, ether by the lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng vpon it or by the knelyng be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, for any other reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes thys: ſo ought we to folowe &amp; fulfyll thys commaundement of the Lorde, and to let the ſettyng of it vp for to be kneled vnto, without the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyuing therof, fal, as the playne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention of man.</p>
               <p>And yet ſeyng the lorde doeth in the holy ſouper, thorowe hys worde and ſacramente, offre hym ſelfe vnto vs after a ſynguler grace, and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth hymſelfe to be more mercyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye preſent in this ſacrament when it is miniſtred at his holy ſouper, than in other of hys creatures, ſo ſhall we wourſhyp hym there alſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyngly, that is to ſay, fyrſt,<note place="margin">How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> worſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſte in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</note> conceyue an earneſt repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for our ſinnes paſte wyth a ſure fayth by it in hys death and bodye bothe for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon of our ſynnes and for the recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of his own grace and ſtrength
<pb facs="tcp:11356:46"/> to amende theym agayne: and then wyth the ſame fayth receyue it hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and wyth the fallyng downe vp on our knees, and with the ſhewyng of all other corporall reuerence: lyke as we maye reade,<note place="margin">Geneſ. xxiiii. Exo. iiii and .xii.</note> that they of the olde tyme dyd worſhyppe God with the fallyng downe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr knees, and with other tokens of honoure &amp; reuerence, ſo often as he dyd preſent hymſelfe vnto them, after any ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or ſyngular maner, as by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtracyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his word &amp; ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.</p>
               <p>Wherfore thys doth well agree wyth the ſcripture: that ſeynge we haue in the holy ſouper the lord hym ſelfe preſent amongeſt vs, as he was preſent wyth theim of the olde tyme in their ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, that we ſhould worſhippe hym there alſo both with hearte and mynde, and with all the powers and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of oure bodies, as well as they dyd worſhyppe hym ſo in tymes paſt and yet commytted
<pb facs="tcp:11356:46"/> therwith no ydolatrye. But that we ſhoulde therefore reſerue the breade whiche hath bene once at the ſouper, and cauſe the people to lyfte vp han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des and eyes vnto it, as though god were bounde thereunto, whether it dyd miniſter hys worde and ſygny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycation vnto vs after ſuche ſorte as he had appoynted it or no, that can not ſtand wyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God whiche requireth but thys honoure &amp; obedyence onely of vs in thys ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthen our faith by it. The which ſtrengthening of our faith as be it, it can not be wrought into vs by anye other meanes, than by the receyuynge of it onely, after Chriſtes ordynaunce, ſo is it then on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to be worſhipped and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſacrament, and none otherwyſe.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, there can no man ſaye, that the breade and wine ſhuld be Chriſte hym ſelfe comprehenſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye, or naturally bynde hym vnto
<pb facs="tcp:11356:47"/> them, bycauſe they haue bene ones preſented at his holy ſouper. But we muſte nedes graunte this ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be then only a ſigne &amp; token that God doeth preſent vnto vs his very body and blode, when it doeth preſent and ſpeake theſe wordes vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs: take, eate, this is my bodye: take, drynke, thys is my blode &amp;c. And therfore as we can not ſay that we receaue theſe wordes by the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment but when we receyue it corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in and at the holi ſouper, ſo can we not ſay that we do reſerue Chriſt amongeſt vs after the ſouper, but by the applyenge of our hole lyues to his holy wyll,<note place="margin">How to reſerue Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongeſt vs.</note> as by the often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuyng of thys ſacramente, and by the folowyng of his other commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes.</p>
               <p>But to proue the externall wour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppyng of the ſacrament when it was not receyued, all that euer the Pope coulde bryng in out of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:11356:47"/> doctors, was this ſayeng onely of ſainct Auſtyne. No man eateth the fleſhe of Chriſte, that dothe not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe it before. Whiche ſaying we iudge to be right godly ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But that in theſe wordes ſaincte Auſtyne meaned of the worſhyppinge of the ſacrament with handes and knees without the receyuing of it (a thing whiche was vtterly vnknowen in ſaincte Auſtines dayes) and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſpirituall worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of it, is not to be thought. For to worſhyppe the fleſhe of Chriſte can be nothynge elles than with an humble and penitent mynde to ſhew vs to beleue this ſurely of oure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure Chriſtes fleſhe: fyrſte, that he hath offred it vp vpon the croſſe, &amp; inſtituted this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to aſſure vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame one offeri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remiſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſinnes for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,<note place="margin">To wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fleſhe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt.</note> &amp; did therfore preſent &amp; offre vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs frely the grace &amp; good wyll of
<pb facs="tcp:11356:48"/> God by it, for to helpe vs to beleue ſurely in it both for the remiſſion of our ſynnes, and for the receyuing of hys grace and ſtrengthe to amende them agayne: and then, humblye to receyue thys ſacrament in the ſame fayth, &amp; wyth a good purpoſe to vſe the grace geuen vs by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame to the vtter mortifying of our owne fleſhe. Thys is the trewe wourſhyppynge of the fleſhe of Chriſt, ether at the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyuyng of thys ſacrament or at the exercyſyng of any other of Chriſtes commaundementes. And thus maye we wourſhyppe the fleſhe of Chriſte and receyue it alſo thorow fayth and by the applyeng of our ſelues to his hole lawes, as to the hearynge or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of his holy worde, or to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſynge of faſt, prayer, and almoſe dedes, euen aſwell as by the recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of this holy ſacrament. And therfore to wourſhyppe the fleſhe of Chriſt before we do eate it, can be no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyng
<pb facs="tcp:11356:48"/> elles, than to beleue ſurely in the death and reſurrection of it. Fyrſt, and than to obey and folowe his commaundementes with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygence. And that we can not wour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe the fleſhe of Chriſte anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than thus as is aforeſaid, neither yet reſerue or comprehende it in the ſacramentes for to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped, though the elementes or crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of that breade and wyne why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath bene ones vſed at the holye ſouper, maye be reſerued, but onelye when they do miniſtre vnto vs theſe wordes: take eate, take, drynke, lyke as God hath appoynted them, maye eaſely be perceyued by the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of baptyſme. Vnto the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we iudge no honoure to be due but onely when the water doeth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfie vs that our ſoules are waſſhed within, thorowe the body and blode of Chriſt, by hauyng it powred vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our bodyes outwardely, in token or
<pb facs="tcp:11356:49"/> remembraunce of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ But to this the Pope hathe ſayde: the water of baptiſme ought not to haue ſo muche honoure done vnto it, as the ſacrament of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and blod of Chriſt, both bycauſe Chriſte is not naturally and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially in that water, and alſo bicauſe there is no ſuche chaunge of that wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter into the bodye and blod of Chriſt as there is in the breade which hath bene at the holy ſouper.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwere.</label> After what ſorte hys chaunge was, or howe he thought Chriſte to be preſente in the holy ſacrament of Baptiſme, I cannot tell. But this I am ſure of, that yf the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of baptime be miniſtred a right, and accordynge to the ordynance of Chriſte, there baptyſeth by it: God the father, God the ſonne, and God
<pb facs="tcp:11356:49"/> the holye ghoſte. Theſe .iii. doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe are geuen in the name of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme. And howe it ſhoulde be then, that Chriſt is not as natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and ſubſtancially preſente there, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, is to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at. But doubtleſſe as bothe theſe ſacramentes are the ordynaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of Chriſte, and inſtytuted both for one purpoſe, (as towchynge to theyr effecte) ſo is he as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally preſente wyth the one as wyth the other: and hys preſence is to be honoured in the one, lyke as it is in the other</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ The Pope hymſelfe doeth graunte the ſubſtaunce and effecte of Baptyſme to conſyſte chieflye in the miniſtracion of theſe woordes: I Baptyſe thee in the name of the father &amp; cetera. And yet he wyll not graunte the ſubſtaunce and effecte of thys other ſacramente to conſyſt chiefly in the miniſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of
<pb facs="tcp:11356:50"/> theſe wordes likewiſe: take, eate, this is my body &amp;c. take, drynke, this is my blod. &amp;c. but ſaith that the bread is alwaye the body of Chriſte, yf it hath bene once conſecrated, whether it be mynyſtred or hanged vp for a ſhewe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwere.</label> Fyrſt, that the ſubſtance of holye baptyme doeth not chefly alone but alſo holly conſyſt in the myniſtracy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the wordes appointed vnto it, is good to be knowen. For excepte there be a perſon baptiſed with the water,<note place="margin">The ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of baptime conſyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtration of the wordes onely.</note> in the name of the father, the ſonne, and the holye ghoſte, the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it ſelfe is of none effect. For as Saynt Auſten ſaith: when the word commeth together wyth the water, then is there a ſacramente. By the whiche ſayeng he meaned as yf he woulde haue ſayde thus: when theſe wordes. I baptiſe the in the name of the father, the ſonne, &amp; the holy goſt,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:50"/> are miniſtred by the water of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, &amp; receyued with beleue of him, vnto whome they are miniſtred, then is there a ſacramente preſented and geuen vnto him. Whereupon this doctor ſaide further thus alſo: in the water doth the word purifye. Take awaye the worde, and what is it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other than water. Beholde, without theſe wordes be miniſtred by the water: I baptyſe the in the name of the father, &amp;c. the water of it ſelfe is of none effecte. And where is then I praye you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of ſo many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynges and brethinges as wer wont to be made ouer the font, when there dyd none yet receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effect of theſe wordes together with the water? but as theſe wordes of baptiſing, which onely make the water of it of effecte, can not be receyued, but when the water is miniſtred to one that is baptiſed in dede, ſo doth the hole ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and ſubſtaunce of this holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb facs="tcp:11356:51"/> of baptyme, conſyſt chiefely and onely in the myniſtryng of the wordes.</p>
               <p>And eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo doth the hole ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and effecte of both theſe .ii. ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, baptyme &amp; the ſouper of Lorde, conſyſt and ſtande in the miniſtring of the wordes that Chriſte hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed vnto them. For yf they be not ſo vſed, that the worde maye go together with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtring of them, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame forme and maner that theyr lorde and maiſter did miniſtre them him ſelfe, and appointed or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned vs to do it after him, but are altered of vs, then are they not hys ſacramentes, but our owne inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Wherfore as in the ſacrament of baptiſme there muſte be preſente fyrſte the miniſtre, whoſe fayth is ſo farre forthe required that he do ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to myniſtre it both according to Chriſtes ordinaunce, and for the
<pb facs="tcp:11356:51"/> ſame purpoſe alſo that he dyd inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute it, to wete, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtyrryng vp of fayth in hym for the fre remiſſion of theyr ſynnes: and then there muſte be preſent alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſone which may haue it myniſtred vnto hym: and thyrdlye there muſte be wyth bothe theſe in lykewyſe, the ſacrament of baptyme, whych is not the water of it ſelfe, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyppyng in, or the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng on of the water vpon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone together wyth theſe wordes: I baptiſe the in the name of the father, the ſonne, and the holy gooſt: euen ſo is it wyth the ſouper of the Lorde. For there muſte be preſent fyrſt, the myniſtre, whoſe fayth is thus farre forth requyred, that he do entende to ſtyrre vp a trewe fayth in Chriſte, and that by the myniſtrynge of it accordynge to hys ordynaunce, and there muſt be preſent alſo them that wyll receyue the holy ſouper, and
<pb facs="tcp:11356:52"/> then the ſacrament,<note place="margin">The ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance of the holy ſouper doth con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyſt in the mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtryng of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> whiche is not the breade and wyne of themſelues, but the miniſtrynge of the breade and wyne together wyth theſe wordes: take, eate, this is my bodye &amp;c. take drinke, this is my blod &amp;c. do thys in the remembraunce of me. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeyng oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt hathe ioyned all theſe wordes and the miniſtrynge of theym to gether thus, and commaunded vs to do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ſame thynge that he dyd hym ſelfe, in the remembraunce bothe of hys paſſyon and of inſtytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge thys ſacramente, wyth all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynges that he hathe done or doeth for vs, ſo ſhall it not be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for vs ether to deuyde or parte in ſundre theſe holye woordes and the miniſtringe of theym together with the ſacrament makyng the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſacramentall wordes to be onely theſe: thys is my body. Or to take
<pb facs="tcp:11356:52"/> the breade and wyne for the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of hys bodye and blod, though they had bene once prepared for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when theſe other wordes: take, eate, take, drynke, do thys in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of me, are excluded frome theym. For theſe wordes: take, eate, take, drynke, and do thys in the remembraunce of me, do make the ſacrament to be of effecte vnto vs, in ſhewynge thys, that he would neuer haue put vs in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thus,<note place="margin">Theſe wordes: take, eate, &amp; drynke do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament aſwel as theſe: this is my body</note> of hys bodye breakyng &amp; blod ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng for our ſinnes, if he would not haue vs to gather firſt a ſure fayth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remiſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al our ſinnes, by the ſame, at al ſuche tymes as they were miniſtred and ſpoken vnto vs accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng to his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, aſwel as he woulde by theſe other wordes: thys is my bodye, declare what it is that we ſhal receiue afterwarde. Wherefore as we do fyrſte gather
<pb facs="tcp:11356:53"/> a ſure faythe in oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſte,<note place="margin">We do fyrſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fayth in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſyon of al our ſynnes by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſte ſpeake the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when he wyll pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſente the ſacra. And we doſtreng then the ſame faith by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuyng of it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes</note> by the hearyng of this hys commaundement: take, eate, take, drinke, and do this in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of me, as well as we do by the other wordes whiche declare the ſacramente to be his bodye that we ſhall then receyue, ſo ſhoulde theſe wordes be alwayes ſpoken together vnto the people, when the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t maye be miniſtred with them alſo. Leſt the wordes whych do declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacra. to be his body, myght elles be ſpoken to our da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, yf the other wordes whych do declare his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in preſentyng of it vnto vs, dyd not fyrſt geue vs thys fayth before, that he woulde neuer ſo haue ſayd &amp; done yf he wold not haue ſhewed by the ſame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his body &amp; blode was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the remiſſion of our ſynnes. And yet the ſchole doctours, beyng deceyued thorowe the abuſe whyche was crepte in by the reſeruynge
<pb facs="tcp:11356:53"/> of that breade whych had bene ones prepared at the ſouper, made the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall wordes onely theſe: thys is my bodye.</p>
               <p>Now out of al this, maye euery good chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man perceyue, that the hole vertue, ſubſtance, and effecte of this holy ſacramente of the lordes ſouper, doth no leſſe conſiſt &amp; ſtande onely in the miniſtring of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and ſacrament together, lyke as he dyd vſe them him ſelfe, than doth the holy ſacrament of baptime, and that theſe .ii. ſacramentes are in this poynt bothe of one nature, and not vnlyke, that is to ſaye, the water of baptime is a ſacramente when theſe wordes are miniſtred by it: I bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe the in the name &amp; cetera. and the breade and wine is a ſacrament whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe wordes are miniſtred by it of Chriſt hym ſelfe (though yet by the mouthe of a miniſtre appointed): take, eate, this is my body &amp; cetera.
<pb facs="tcp:11356:54"/> take, drynke, this is my blode &amp;c. and do this in the remembraunce of me. Wherefore they are nether of them ſacramentes but when they are in miniſtrynge of the woordes whyche Chriſte appoynted to them, althoughe the Pope woulde haue that breade which hath bene ones at the holy ſouper to be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged vp, and borne about in proceſſions as a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, for to mayntayne therwith all thys abuſe: that it myghte be corporally worſhypped, as though that ſhulde be more to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honouryng of the ſacrament then to haue it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to be receyued ſpiritually. Let euery good chriſten man iudge thys by the worde of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ But thou ſayeſt: yf the hangyng vp of the ſacramente, and the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it about, for to be corporally worſhypped ſhoulde be layde a ſyde as an abuſe, ſo ſhulde we condemne therwith, as manifeſt ydolatrers,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:54"/> both all them that haue ſo worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped it wythout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> receyuyng, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo that do ſo worſhyppe it yet in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther countres.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwere.</label> Though the worſhypping of it, as it hath ben vſed, ſhulde be layde a ſyde as an abuſe, yet is there not therwithall condemned all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that haue done, or do yet wour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe it ſo in other countres. But therwithall is conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned thys abuſe, that men ſhulde not holde, take and receiue this holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as Chriſt hath ordeyned it to be taken, to the ſtrengthening of theyr faith in him, both for theyr ſynnes paſt, &amp; for the receyuynge of hys grace to amende them againe, but to ſhew it, to ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge it vp, and to beare it aboute, to haue it corporally worſhypped onely. Whych kynde of honouryng it, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out the receyuyng therof, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde hath made no mencion of it, neither
<pb facs="tcp:11356:55"/> by worde nor dede in all his holy ſcriptures, and doth therfore ſerue to the vaine truſtyng in the inuencyon of man, ſo hathe he forboden it as a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g moſt abhominable in his ſight. This abuſe is to be condemned, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we do not therwith co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne the hole church of Chriſt, that ether hath or dothe yet abyde in the ſame vnwittinglye. For as many of the children of god as hath or dothe yet folowe this abuſe, not knowynge any better but beynge ſeduced by their paſtors, that do they not as the membres of Ieſu Chriſte, and of his churche,<note place="margin">The me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bres of the churche may wel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re but not as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of Chriſte.</note> but as they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfite and ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſons, which ignoraunce god oure heauenlye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for his ſonnes ſake Ieſu Chriſt, ſhal forgeue them withal their other offences lyke as he doth forgeue vs our dayly ſynnes alſo, when ſo euer they or we do repent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ But for an excuſe of this clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:11356:55"/> holyneſſe, the Pope ſayeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: it can be none abuſe, nor anye euell thyng, what ſo euer is, of good deuotion, done to the honoure of God and to the hauynge of hys ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes in hygher reuerence.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwere.</label> Thys were verye well ſpoken yf all men knewe truely what good deuotion were. Whyche doutleſſe can be in nothynge, where Goddes worde and commaundement is not. King Vzia did of a good deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as he thought) ſaue certaine of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle which he toke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his enemies,<note place="margin">ii. para. xxviii.</note> to do ſacrifice vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all, for the great victory he had geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym. And yet bycauſe it was not according to gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſo did, he was puiniſhed for it. And therefore we maye not loke what we thynke to be good deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vſe it, but we muſte cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the beſt deuotion which doth moſt agree w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes.
<pb facs="tcp:11356:56"/> Wherfore let vs count this to be the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chiefe honouryng of this ſacrament to receyue it with ſuch a pure faith as cauſeth both repentaunce for our former ſynnes, &amp; a good purpoſe to amende theym agayne, to ſprynge forth in vs. Well, thus haue we proued that this ſacramente, oughte not to be reſerued for to be corporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wourſhypped alſo, as the Arke was.</p>
               <p>And as thys was a great abuſe to ſette vp the ſacrament or to carye it aboute in proceſſyons for to haue it corporally wourſhypped without the preſentyng of it to be corporally receyued, ſayinge ones in the yeare onely, ſo was thys no leſſe abuſe, to receyue it than neyther but in one kynde onelye. And that this was alſo an abuſe, conſydre fyrſte, that it muſte nedes be graunted to be an abuſe, to alter anye of Goddes ordinaunces otherwiſe than he vſed
<pb facs="tcp:11356:56"/> them himſelfe,<note place="margin">To vſe a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny thing otherwy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe than the lorde hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, is an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe.</note> and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded them to be vſed of other. Now is it plaine and of al men confeſſed, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde in hys fyrſt ſouper dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate the ſacrament in both kyndes vnto his diſciples, commaundyng them alſo to do the ſame that he himſelfe had done before them. The whiche commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was obſerued, and the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in both kyndes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated for longe tyme in the church after Chriſt, yea and it hath bene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vſed to thys daye in Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia and Gretia. And how it came to paſſe that men of late dayes dyd vſe to receiue it thus in one kynde only, we fynde no good teſtimony. Wher by we iudge it to haue crept in by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> negligence of prieſtes and paſtors.</p>
               <p>But ſeyng the Lorde hath ordey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the breade to be the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his bodye for it ſelfe, and the wyne to be the ſacrament of his blode, we ought to ſpeake of them as he hath
<pb facs="tcp:11356:57"/> ordeyned them, and none otherwyſe. The lorde hath appointed theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des to be myniſtred by the breade: take, eate, thys is my bodye whyche ſhalbe geuen for you. And theſe to be miniſtred by the cuppe: take, drinke, thys cuppe is the newe teſtament in my bloude, whych ſhalbe ſhedde for you and for many, to the remiſſion of ſynnes. And wherfore wyll we then be wyſer then Chriſt hath tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght vs, in ſayinge: the breade alone is the body and blode of Chriſt, and the cuppe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blode and body? in dede in hym ſelfe the lorde hath his body and bloude inſeperable, and geueth them to vs holly together and vnde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uided. Yet as he hath ordeyned the breade for the diſtributyng of hys bodye, and the cuppe for the geuing forth of his bloude, ſo ought we to vſe them, &amp; to ſpeake of them, wyth out any further reaſonyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ But for the miniſtring of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb facs="tcp:11356:57"/> in one kynde onely, and for the mayntenaunce of all other abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes contrarye to goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, the Pope is wont to bryng in thys reaſon: The churche hath in all outwarde thynges power to dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe and ordre, as they ſhall thinke beſt: and therfore thei may kepe this ordynaunce of receyuyng the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in one kynde onely, yf they ſhal thynke it good.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>The aunſwere.</label> The holy churche of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded wyth his ſpirite,<note place="margin">Who be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of chriſt, &amp; what is their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note> hath doutleſſe power to ordre &amp; dyſpoſe all outward thynges in tyme, place, meaſure and maner, ſo farre forth as the ſame may make to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> encreaſe of godlyneſſe amongeſt the people, that is to ſay, deuote people both of the clergye &amp; layte, maye ordre and dyſpoſe the tyme &amp; place that gods wourde and the holye ſacramentes ſhall be myniſtred in, and they maye
<pb facs="tcp:11356:58"/> ordre the maner, meaſure, and tyme of praying together in the church, &amp; appoint the daye and tyme when the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune faſte ſhalbe obſerued of all the people together. In al theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges hath the hole church of Chriſte ful authoritie and power to diſpoſe, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynges myght ſo muche the better for ſuche appointing of tyme, place, meaſure, and maner, be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and holden as Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded them, that is to ſaye, that men myght the more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniently by the appointing of ſuche a place and tyme, heare the worde of God and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue the ſacramentes, and the more quyetly come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende that faſting and prayer was ordeyned for. Out of the whych grounde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church hath euen from the begynnyng made or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunces, both for the worde and ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, and alſo for other god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſes. As for thys ſacrament, that men ſhulde receiue it faſting in
<pb facs="tcp:11356:58"/> the morning (yf neceſſitie dyd not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe requyre) bycauſe that ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſemed, and is, (as euery man wel knoweth) more mete for the ſtyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge vp of deuotyon and earneſt godlyneſſe, than is the tyme after we haue eaten oure full. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſeynge that the commynge to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to the Lordes ſouper is the godlyeſt and moſte holſome worke that one of vs maye exerciſe &amp; vſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> another, ſo hath the church thoughte it good, and to the furtheraunce of muche deuocyon, that it ſhoulde be holden in a place bothe ſeuerall from all other, and alſo with out the vſing of any worldly buſineſſe with it, as not onely ſaint Paule,<note place="margin">i. Cor. x.</note> but all the hole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation of Chriſt alſo, ordeyned that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhulde kepe none other feaſt in the churche, when they wolde go vnto the table of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde, but it alone. Alſo, ſeyng that Chriſt hath not ſhewed by expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb facs="tcp:11356:59"/> what praiers of thankes ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyng, or what other godlye inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions he woulde haue vſed at hys holy ſouper, and dyd yet vſe it hym ſelfe with great plentie of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, therfore ought the church of Chriſt to deſcrybe ſome godlye forme and manner of geuynge inſtructions vnto the people before they come vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the receyuynge of ſo hyghe a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye,<note place="margin">The churche, that is to ſaye, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute people both of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gye in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye countre ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyde for them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues, that all thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges be done af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre.</note> and of rendryng thankes vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to god for it, after they haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it. Wherefore this is the hole authoritie and power that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church hath in the worde and ſacramentes, and other of goddes ordynaunces, that they maye thus, and ſhall with all their diligence, bothe aſwel the Prynces and Magiſtrates the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, as the miniſters of the worde, ordre and dyſpoſe them ſo in tyme, place, meaſure, and maner, that the people therby myght not only haue the more deuocion to vſe them with
<pb facs="tcp:11356:59"/> al feare and reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but alſo come the better to the ſame ende and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of them that they were ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for of god.<note place="margin">The churche hath no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way any of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, no more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it can forbidde vs to faſt or pray.</note> But to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge them vnto any other faſhyon, (as this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament was chaunged from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral receiuing of it into a lokinge glaſſe) or to leaue them vtterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done (lyke as men had left the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of the cuppe in the holy ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per) that authorite hath no man, tyll Chriſt, whiche is the ende that they lead vs vnto, come hym ſelfe. For it can be called no right orderynge or dyſpoſynge of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> encreaſing of any godlineſſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, for to take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cleane away: no more than it can be called a right ordering of our prayers, to ſay we wyll praye trewly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our hertes, though we do wylfully leaue out the praier of the mouthe alſo. Wherfore it muſt nedes be an abuſe to receiue the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in one kinde only, other wiſe than god hath ordeyned it.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11356:60"/>
               <p>Moreouer that we ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue thys ſacrament, in both kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des maye well be perceyued, in that the lorde hym ſelfe, after he had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cuppe into his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, geuen tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, &amp; reached it vnto his diſciples, dyd &amp; that with great feruentneſſe, and wyth more playne and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table wordes, expreſſe our redemtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion in him by the cuppe, then he dyd by the breade or by any other ſacrament. For at baptyme, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded no more to be ſaid then: I baptiſe the in the name of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the ſonne, and the holy gooſt. And at the miniſtryng of the breade of thankes geuyng, no more then: take, eate, thys is my bodye, whyche ſhalbe geuen for you. But at the mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſtring of the cuppe he ſayd, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded other in his name to ſaye: take, drynke, thys cuppe is the new teſtament in my blode, whych ſhalbe ſhedde for you and for many vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11356:60"/> remiſſion of ſynnes. Beholde, good reader, howe comfortable a goſpell our ſauiour Chriſte hathe ordeyned thys ſacrament of wyne to expreſſe. Wherfore it maye well be called the moſte holy and comfortableſt ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all other.<note place="margin">The cup is the moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> For ſeyng it is the worde, when it is myniſtred by the creature, that maketh the creature to be a ſacrament, ſo doth it doutleſſe folowe, that ſo muche the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordes are when they are miniſtred, ſo muche the greater is the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that miniſtreth them And therfore no chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man, yea no aungell from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, oughte to haue taken awaye from the weake &amp; ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full flocke of Chriſt, this moſte com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fortable ſacrament ſpecially ſeyng the lorde hymſelfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded it to be vſed alſo, wyth ſo great feruent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Wherfore he that wolde wyth holde thys ſacrament of wyne from the people in the holy ſouper, ſhulde
<pb facs="tcp:11356:61"/> (as much as in him lyeth) kepe from theym the miniſtration of this holy ghoſpell, that Chriſte hathe ſhedde hys moſte precyous blode for them. For althoughe we do in dede receiue euen the ſame thynge before by the breade when it doeth miniſtre vnto vs the bodye of Chriſte, that we do afterwarde when we receyue the cup whiche miniſtreth vnto vs his blod: yet as he that loſeth the profyte of them bothe agayne, whiche wyll not for all thys geue hymſelfe, wyth all dylygence, vnto faſte, prayer, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſſe dedes and all other Godlye exercyſes, but wylfully foloweth the workes of the fleſhe: ſo doeth he loſe the profyte that he had receyued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the breade whiche miniſtred vnto him the bodye of Chriſte, that wylfullye wyll refuſe to receyue the wyne, whiche ſhoulde alſo myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vnto him his blode.</p>
               <p>Wherefore yf it be an abuſe to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte
<pb facs="tcp:11356:61"/> gods commaundementes, when oportunite ſerueth vs to obey the ſame, than muſte it nedes be a great abuſe to refuſe the receyuyng of the holy cuppe of thankes geuyng, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is miniſtred in the holy ſouper. But bycauſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld not ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſe vpon the trew receyuing of this holy ſacrament of the body and blod of Chriſt, ether in one kynde or in both, the pope was wont to bring in this argument chiefly.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ This ſacrament of the bodye and blode of Chriſte (ſayeth he) maye aſwel be receyued ſpiritually by cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge to remembraunce that Chriſt hath dyed for vs when we do but loke vpon it, as it maye be outwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely: though we ſhoulde receyue it ones in the yere outwardely alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwere.</label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11356:62"/> To ſaye that the ſacrament may aſwell be receyued ſpiritually, as it maye be corporallye or outwardlye, muſte nedes be a wonderful ſaying. For turne it what waye ye wyll, and it ſhalbe yet holly agaynſt Chriſt &amp; his manifeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement. For yf ye vnderſtande by the ſpirituall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuynge of this ſacrament that it muſte be receyued in trew fayth,<note place="margin">The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued both cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually.</note> but yet corporally alſo, then is that the onely receyuyng of it accordyng to goddes ſpirituall ordinaunce, and none other. But yf you vnderſtande your ſaying of ſuche a ſpirituall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuyng of thys ſacra. as is wyth out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corporall receyuyng of it alſo, ſo can not that be the receyuyng of it according to goddes ſpiritual or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce. For he gaue the bread vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to hys diſciples and commaunded them to take, and eate it, &amp; that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally alſo, and in like maner gaue he them the cuppe to drynke. And
<pb facs="tcp:11356:62"/> therfore as it is manyfeſtly agaynſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of Chriſt, to make a gaſynge ſtocke of the ſacrament &amp; not to receiue it, in ſaying thou canſt call aſmuche to mynde when thou doeſt but ſe it, as the Lorde hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned to put into thy minde by the corporall receyuyng of it after hys moſte louyng and ſpirituall inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo is there no ſpirituall recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of this ſacrament but to take it corporally with ſuche a ſpirit and fayth, as ſtyrreth vs both to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce for our ſynnes paſt,<note place="margin">To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of god in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it corporal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, what it is.</note> and alſo to amende them agayne by the hum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble folowyng of hys lawes.</p>
               <p>And yet for the mayntenaunce of a ſpirituall receyuyng of thys ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, many haue brought forth this ſaying alſo of ſaint Auſtyne: <hi>Crede et manducaſti,</hi> that is to ſaye, beleue &amp; thou haſt receyued. The whych ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath yet bene dyuerſely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, lyke as the appetites of men
<pb facs="tcp:11356:63"/> are dyuerſe. For many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whych wyl ſeme to fauour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god, haue vnderſtande it thus: yf a man beleue trewly in Chriſt it forceth ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel for the receiuing of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, a man maye be ſaued well ynoughe wythout it, ſay they: and ſo they are become as negligent in receyuyng of thys holy ſacrament as euer they were before. But of ſuche I woulde fayne knowe, what the corporall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuyng of thys ſacrament is, and where to it ſerueth, yf to beleue in Chriſt be the onely receyuyng of it. Other ſome agayne, (as the Pope enſpecially) hath ſayde, that yf a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleue trwly vpon the ſacrament he hath fulfilled theſe wordes of ſainct Auſtyne: <hi>Crede et manducaſti,</hi> that is to ſaye, beleue and thou haſte recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. But to all ſuche I aunſwere, that we maye not beleue vpon the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as yf it were able to worke or geue vs our ſaluation of it ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:63"/> but we muſt beleue vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt and vpon the merites of his paſſion, the vertue and ſtrength whereof he ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs in thys ſacrament. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when ſaint Auſtyne ſpake theſe wordes: <hi>Crede et manducaſti,</hi> that is to ſaye, beleue &amp; thou haſt receyued, it muſt nedes be that he meaned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr beleue that coulde not come vnto the vſe of the ſacrament. Vnto whome he myght wel ſay, <hi>Quid paras uentrem et dentes, crede et manducaſti,</hi> that is to ſay, what doeſt thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare either belye or teeth, beleue in Chriſt, &amp; thou haſt eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thyng that he wolde geue the by the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t yf thou myghteſt come vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to it.<note place="margin">We muſt vſe all theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tually, &amp; yet corpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rally al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</note> For if we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not come vnto this ſacra. for lacke of oportunitie, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faſt by meanes of weaknes, nor pray for lacke of tonge, nether ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue almoſe for lacke of ſubſtance, yet yf we beleue ſurely in Ieſus Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:64"/> this ſame fayth ſhalbe rekened vnto vs for al righteouſnes. But againe, yf we may vſe ether any of theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, or can come vnto this ſacra. we ought to vſe it, and that as often as it is preſented, (except our delytyng in ſinne fear vs to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary) &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make a gaſing ſtocke of it, as yf we could receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth therof by what meanes we wold, nor yet thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vs to haue no nede of it bycauſe we do ſumwhat beleue in Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. We haue the holy goſpel, tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe the whych we may continually eate and receyue Chriſt ſpiritually: and yet when the ſacra. is preſented, we ſhall to the furtheryng of oure fayth and to the encreaſyng of oure obedience towardes goddes lawes, vſe it alſo, &amp; that after the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that the lorde vſed it hym ſelfe, &amp; not turne or peruert the ſacra. into anye other vſe, but abyde by theſe plaine wordes of the lorde: take, eate
<pb facs="tcp:11356:64"/> &amp;c. take and drynke &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ But thou ſayeſt: oure ſauiour Chriſt hath not bounde him ſelfe or the workes of our ſaluation vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny outwarde worke or ceremonye, and therefore it is not neceſſarye to our ſaluacion to receyue this ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but at our lybertye.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwer.</label> Vndoubted it is that our ſauioure Chriſt hath not bounde his grace &amp; the workes of oure ſaluacion vpon any outwarde worke or ceremonye, but we maye receyue and eate to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng lyfe, Chriſt our lord, that trew heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly fode, thorow his word, not only with out this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but with out all other his ordinaunces alſo. For yf we can nether haue the vſe of them, or not haue them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the inſtitucion of Chriſt, yet yf we do beleue theſe wordes truly of the holy goſpel: Chriſt hath dyed for our ſynnes, ſo ſhall we then eate
<pb facs="tcp:11356:65"/> the fleſhe of Ieſu Chriſt and drinke hys bloude to euerlaſtyng lyfe, euen aſwell as we had had the vſe of all hys ordinaunces. But therwithall, when Chriſt ſendeth vs oportunitie of tyme and place, and that we maye conueniently come together in hys name, and holde his holy ſouper, yf we do not then holde the ſame, &amp; that euen after his owne faſſhion and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement, ſo can or maye thys ſprynge of none other occaſion then that we do not aryght knowe Ieſu Chriſt our ſauiour in thys his holy ordinaunce and commaundement of the holye ſouper,<note place="margin">To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in Chriſte a ryght re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyrethe our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des all his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> as oure onelye God and ſauiour. For we do not beleue aryght that he hath ordei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded vs, lyke as in all other, ſo in thys ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo, that, whych ſhal ſerue vs certeynly (yf we wil vſe it onely ſo, as &amp; wherunto he hath ordeined and ſet it forth) to our ſaluation, in furtheryng more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly
<pb facs="tcp:11356:65"/> oure healthfull receyuyng or eatyng of his fleſſhe and blode by it: but we holde the corrupt iudgement of man to be wyſer and more careful for oure ſaluation then our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſte, the euerlaſtyng wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the father, and the whyche was yet ſo deſyrous of oure health, that he did not onely beſtowe his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye and blode for vs vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, but hath prouided thys ſacrament for to geue vs the ſame effectuallye by it alſo.</p>
               <p>But two cauſes ſpeciallye there are wherwyth the Pope hath letted the ſymple people from receyuynge the ſacrament according to Chriſtes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement. The fyrſt was, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he taught (by makyng of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces for the ſame) that the prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes myght vſe the holye ſouper of the Lorde priuatelye for them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and that they myghte ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vſe alſo as many Maſſes in
<pb facs="tcp:11356:66"/> their churches vpon one daye, or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as they lyſt. The ſeconde, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the prieſtes were not commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to teache the people, that it was goe, &amp; neglygence, and worthye to be much reproued in a trew chriſten man, to be preſente at the ſouper of the lorde, and yet not to receyue the ſacramente. The whiche .ii. cauſes doubtleſſe are not only contrarye to the dewtie and ſeruice that god doth in his word require both of the prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes and people, but alſo to the vſe that hathe ben in the olde and pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue churche afore times. And yet to ſtablyſhe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt cauſe and errour, the Pope hath brought in this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ The lorde hath inſtituted this ſacramente, that there myghte and ſhoulde receyue it, who ſo dothe of a pure herte deſyre it. The whiche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre ſhall neyther by the multitude nor feweneſſe of the people, be hyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.
<pb facs="tcp:11356:66"/> And therfore (ſaith he) may any prieſt pryuately &amp; for him ſelf alone, vſe this ſacra. when ſo euer he doeth with a pure herte deſyre it, thoughe there be no man to be comunycated with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwer.</label> That the ſacrament was of the lord inſtituted,<note place="margin">The ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per of the lord is not bownde to any tyme, place, or people: and yet the faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full oughte not to holde it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than the lorde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> that there might and ſhoulde receyue it, whoſoeuer of a pure herte and good deuotion dyd deſyre it, muſt nedes be graunted. But to deſire it wyth a pure hearte and good deuocion can doutleſſe be none other thinge, than to deſyre it accordynge to the ordynaunce and inſtitucion of the lorde. Nowe is it verely the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lord that the faythfull ſhall in commune and beyng gathered together, receyue it one with an other, as the lorde dyd holde it him ſelfe at the fyrſt, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded it of other to be holden: like as ſainct Paule wel witneſſeth,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:67"/> and concludeth vpon this, that it is not the holdynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſouper, when it is not kept in commune, but euery companye for it ſelfe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon he learned and exhorted the Corinthians doynge the contrarye, to tarye one for another,<note place="margin">i. Cor. xi.</note> and ſo to holde it in commen together.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ Thou ſayeſt: yf this ordinaunce of Paule ſhoulde be obſerued of all men, than were the ſycke folke lyke to be euell ſeene vnto, whiche can not come vnto the churche to receyue the ſacrament there in commune.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>¶ The aunſwer.</label> Bycauſe the ſycke folke can not come vnto the churche, therefore oughte the Churche, thorowe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne of their miniſters and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres, to come vnto them, and ſo to holde a communion with them at home in their own houſes, rather tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo godly an ordinaunce ſhoulde be broken. But yf it ſhoulde ſo chaunce
<pb facs="tcp:11356:67"/> that this ordynaunce of receyuynge the ſacra. one with another in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune, could not ſo be kept for lacke of tyme, and perſones conueniente,<note place="margin">Chriſte him ſelfe ſhewed an enſam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of this in healyng a ſike ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the ſabbothe day. Mar. ii.</note> than maye the miniſtre dyſpence w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ordinaunce in time of neceſſitie, and preferre the ſuccouringe of the ſycke mannes conſcience, before the obſeruing of any outwarde ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye. But where the people may come together, there ought this godly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce to be obſerued, with al dily<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gence. For thus haue the good holy fathers vſed it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primatiue church alwayes. The whiche did yet, holde the ſouper of the lorde pryuately for them ſelfes in their oratories, (which were lytle chapelles in their houſes) when they could not haue the people to gether to the ſacramente and had yet a good deuocion to holde the holy ſouper, though not alone but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their deuout brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: like as we may rede of ſaincte Vlrichus and other
<pb facs="tcp:11356:68"/> holy fathers and godly byſhoppes, whiche had their priuate maſſes in their owne houſes, but not without communicantes.</p>
               <p>Wherfore ſeing it is the ordynaunce of the lorde that we ſhould holde the holy ſouper one with another in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune, as Paule well witneſſeth, and that it hath ben alwayes vſed to be holden ſo of the moſt holy martyrs, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſours and other godly fathers, tyll nowe of late, it can be no good deuocion to deſyre to receyue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t after another ordre tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god dyd bothe vſe it him ſelfe, and gaue commaundement to haue it vſed of other, ſeynge there can no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amend his ordre and faſhion in it. Yf a man do deſyre to haue his deuocion exer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſed and ſtrenghthened through the vſynge of godly thinges, he maye vſe ſuche thinges as god hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned for euery mannes ſodein ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie: as the hearinge or redyng of
<pb facs="tcp:11356:68"/> the holy ſcripture, or he may deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teli geue him ſelfe to faſt, praier, and almoſſe dedes. In the whiche godly exerciſes, a trewe and deuoute faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man, maye aſwell receyue and eate that heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly breade, Chriſt our lorde, as in the holy ſouper. But yf he haue deuocion to eate the ſouper of the lorde, ſo let him tary for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregation y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with the eatyng therof together with them in commune, he may profeſſe and ſhewe, that as the breade is made of many graynes which miniſtreth vnto hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verye body of Chriſt, &amp; the wine of manye grapes whiche miniſtreth forthe his blod, ſo wil he be of one mynde, wyl, &amp; power with all them ſpeciallye, that receyueth it together with him.</p>
               <p>Now is it trew alſo, that there is mencion made in the olde doctors, both of the Grekes and Latins, that the people vſed in their dayes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the ſacrament ſome at Eaſter
<pb facs="tcp:11356:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11356:69"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11356:70"/> onely, ſome twyſe or thryſe in the yeare, and ſome oftener, but very few dayly, where the maſſe was yet daily obſerued. But yet can not this proue tha t men haue kept the ſouper of the lorde with out communicantes, and that in euery corner of the churche, like as we haue done. For there was alwayes ſome good deuoute people, beſydes the clerkes and ſcholers which wer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many in eueri church, that tended vpon the miniſtracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacramentes, that would receiue it together with the prieſt. And leſſe any ſhoulde dout of this, I ſhal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfeſtly proue it to haue ben ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ A playne declaration out of the holy ſcripture, and of the vſe of the primatiue church, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhould no maſſe be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherin the ſouper of the lorde is vſed, with out com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municantes.</p>
               <p>The worde of god ſheweth this plaine ynough wher it ſaith: do this
<pb facs="tcp:11356:70"/> in the remembraunce of me. By the whiche wordes we maye well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue that we ought to do euen the ſame thing in the holy ſouper of the lord, that he did him ſelfe in it. Now do the euangelyſtes manyfeſtly wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that he toke the breade and the cuppe in his hande, gaue thankes, &amp; communicated them both vnto hys diſciples, commaundyng them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to take them bothe and receyue them. The which commaundement, beyng ſo manifeſt that nothing can be more plainli ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ought to be ſo highly eſtemed of vs, that we ſhould thinke it vtterly vnlawfull to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle or vſe this ſacrament otherwyſe than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord hath done w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it him ſelfe. Wherefore this plaine &amp; earneſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt ſhalbe ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for to declare vnto al Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that to holde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord with out co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municantes, that is to ſay, wythout the myniſtryng or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatyng of
<pb facs="tcp:11356:71"/> it vnto ſome bodye, is not lawfull. And that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy fathers of olde time haue alſo thought it vnlawful may eaſely be perceyued by thys:<note place="margin">The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers make al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wayes mencion of the dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrybu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge &amp; receyu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</note> in that they do at all tymes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they make mention of the ſouper of the Lorde, and ſpeake of it at any tyme fully, make mencion of the halowyng and dyſtributyng of the ſacrament toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as the chiefe parte and ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof. As is to be ſene fyrſt by ſaint Cypriane, who wrytyng of the maſſe brought forth thys enſample for to feare ſuche as were vnworthy from co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng to the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.<note place="margin">Sermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne de lap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſis.</note> When the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune prayers &amp; ceremonies were fully done, and that the deacon had begon offre,<note place="margin">Note how the olde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thys word, of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer.</note> that is to ſay, to offre &amp; preſente the chalice vnto them that were preſent, a certeyne mayde, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe feare of the godly maieſtie, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe had geuen vnto her aunte in the tyme of perſecution parte of it that had ben offered vnto Idolles,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:71"/> turned her face, holdyng her mouthe together, and wolde not receyue the chalice.</p>
               <p>Saint Ambroſe alſo,<note place="margin">Sermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne .viii. in pſal. cxviii.</note> wrytyng of the holy ſouper of the Lorde, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the people to the receyuyng of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with theſe wordes: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy ſouper is prepared, ſe thou ſtande readye, that thou mayſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue a preſeruation, and that thou mayſt receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Ieſu Chriſt And thus is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſouper ſet forth by the ſame Ambroſe alſo, libr. v. ca. i. ii. iii. Where he ſheweth playnly that the folke, when they dyd holde the holy ſouper, dyd come vp vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alter, to receyue the bodye &amp; blode.<note place="margin">Lib. ii. retract. xi.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And ſaint Auſtyne, ſpeakyng of the ſonges that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſed by the alter, &amp; makyng mencion of the holy ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the lorde, as it was holden in thoſe dayes, wryteth, that men haue ſonge pſalmes before the offeryng, or as that was dyſtributed whyche
<pb facs="tcp:11356:72"/> was offred.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſ. lix.</note>He wrytyng alſo ad Paulinam, and ſpeakyng of the prayer of the maſſe, ſetteth together the halowing and breakyng of the bread that was for to be dyſtributed, &amp; ſayeth, that all theſe thynges were concluded wyth prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. ii. cap. xviii</note>The ſame ſaint Auſten wrytyng contra Fauſtum ſayeth thus: We chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men do kepe the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the offerynge of Chriſte wyth the offeryng <hi>et participationae,</hi> that is to ſaye, with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune partakyng of the body and blode of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>By theſe ſayinges now, euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeeth wel, that wyth them of the olde tyme, the dyſtributyng &amp; receyuyng of the ſacramente was taken forthe effect and ſubſtaunce of the holy ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per. And wythout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whych they dyd not vſe the halowyng or offering of the h. ſacra, but dyd only blyſſe &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe it with thankes geuyng, that it
<pb facs="tcp:11356:72"/> myght be dyſtributed &amp; offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other that were preſent. So that the lay people dyd alwayes vſe it in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune together wyth the prieſtes. Whereupon that holy father Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome dyd ſaye:<note place="margin">Homel. xviii. vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the epiſtle to the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inthians</note> that in the h. ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per there ſhalbe ſet forth vnto al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are preſent, one bodye and one cuppe. And the prieſtes ſhall haue it (ſaieth he) in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune with the folke.</p>
               <p>And further ſayd he: the prieſtes do ſtande in vayne at the alter,<note place="margin">ſermone .iii. ad E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</note> and daylye offerynge is done in vayne, where no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate with them.</p>
               <p>And he wrytyng vpon the epiſtle to the Hebrewes ſayde thus alſo:<note place="margin">Lione<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> xvii. to the Heb.</note> I do not ſaye that it is ynough to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy ſelfe .xl. dayes to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion at Eaſter, as yf I dyd forbyd the therby the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion at any ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of the yeare, but I wyll thou go alwayes vnto it wyth trewe godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11356:73"/>
               <p>Nowe ſeyng this holy doctour Chriſoſtome affirmeth both that the prieſtes do ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alter in vayne, where no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate wyth them, and alſo that he woulde haue men at al tymes of the yere to go vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the ſacrament in trew godlyneſſe, it is to be thought, that yf thys holy byſſhop had had none of the clerkes nor of the lay people to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate wyth hym, that he woulde not haue kept the ſouper of the Lorde.<note place="margin">By bliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge of the folke was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the recy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyng of the good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of god ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed forth in oure ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour Chriſte, wherby the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were ſo ſtirred to faith, that thei were blyſſed therby.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In actis concilii Toletani</hi> haue we, as certeyne prieſtes had begonne to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate by and by for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, ſo ſoone as they had ſayd the prayer of the Lorde, before they dyd blyſſe the folke how that in the ſame cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell it was ordeyned, that when the prayer of the Lorde (called in latyne the <hi>pater noſter</hi>) was ſayde, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of the folke ſhuld folow, &amp; that then fyrſt the holy ſacrament ſhould be receyued, &amp; that after this ordre:
<pb facs="tcp:11356:73"/> the prieſtes ſhoulde receiue it before the alter, the clerkes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quere, and the people without the quere. In the whiche counſell there was alſo ſet forth a reformacyon, and an order deſcrybed for the ſaying of meſſe. Wherby we maye plainly ſee, howe that the holy fathers in thoſe dayes,<note place="margin">All the Canons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer haue ben made for the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng of Maſſe, do wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacra. to be a ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy all parte thereof. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the olde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer knew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maſſe ſayd with the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating therof</note> dyd take the communicatyng of the folke with the ſacramente, to be the chiefeſt, parte, effecte, and ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the meſſe. Yea and not onli is this founde by all the olde holy fathers of the prymatiue churche, but it is ſtablyſhed alſo with al the ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of holy counſelles, where the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye can neuer be founde in any good author, but ſpeciall in no cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel. And that doth all the orders and canons made for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayeng of meſſe, not onely amongeſt the Grekes, but the Latiniſtes alſo, moſt plainly wyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe: lyke as we maye well ſee by the forme and canon whiche hathe
<pb facs="tcp:11356:74"/> ben dayly vſed amongeſt vs for the ſame. As where it is ordeyned in the canon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt, ſhould after the conſecration, ſpeake alwayes theſe wordes: we meke men do deſyer the, O almyghtye god, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde theſe thinges, throughe the handes of thy holy aungelles, to be caryed vp to thy hyghe alter, in the ſight of thy diuine maieſtye, that we all, whiche of the communion of this alter, ſhal receyue the holy body and blode of thy ſonne, may be replenyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with al grace &amp; thankefulneſſe. Seynge nowe that this praier was made for a part of the canon &amp; rule which was ſet forth for the right or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre of ſayenge maſſe, &amp; was therfore to be continually ſaide, when ſo euer there was any maſſe holden, it is doutleſſe good to perceyue, that when thys prayer was made firſte, and a ryghte, it was not made to
<pb facs="tcp:11356:74"/> be ſayde in mockage to the dyuyne maieſtye, lyke as it hathe nowe for longe bene vſed, but bycauſe the people in thoſe dayes ſhoulde vſe to receyue the bodye &amp; bloude of Chriſt wyth the prieſt, when ſo euer there was any maſſe ſayd.</p>
               <p>Marke theſe .iiii. wordes ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in thys prayer whych was thus in Latyne: <hi>Vt quotquot ex hac altaris participatione corpus et ſanguinem filii tui ſumpſerimus,</hi> that is to ſaye, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche the that as many of vs, firſt as haue receyued, ſeconde, of thys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the alter, thyrde, the body and bloud of thy ſonne, fourth, may be replenyſſhed wyth all grace and thankefulneſſe. Whyche prayer can not be ſayd of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ryght, where the body and bloud of Chriſt is not ſo receyued as the Lorde appointed it to be done, by takyng and eatyng of the breade, and by drynkynge
<pb facs="tcp:11356:75"/> of the cup at an holy ſouper. And vpon the receyuynge of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thus, goeth many of the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers alſo, whiche were made to be ſayd after the communion, and wer therfore called in latyne <hi>Poſt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionem,</hi> wherof ſome of them dyd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyne thus: <hi>Sacramenta que ſumpſimus</hi> that is to ſay, that ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes which we haue receyued. <hi>Item miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria que ſumpſimus,</hi> that is to ſaye, the miſteries which we haue taken, and ſuche lyke. Alſo in the canon and ordre whiche Dioniſius ſet forthe for the ſayenge of Maſſe, and in other olde formes and canons made both amongeſt the Gekes and La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiniſtes, there is playnely declared that the miniſtrynge of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment to the people, was alwayes a ſpecyall parte of holdynge the holy ſouper. For in all theſe formes and canons there is an ordre ſet foorth howe the prieſtes ſhoulde exhort
<pb facs="tcp:11356:75"/> the people to the receyuynge of the ſacramente and howe they ſhoulde miniſtre the ſame vnto them.</p>
               <p>Therefore is it true, and ſhall remayne true for euer, that as the ordynaunce of oure ſauyour Ieſus Chriſte is manyfeſt and plaine that men ſhold alwaies when his ſouper is in hande, take and eate the bread and drynke of the cuppe, euen ſo hathe the holy fathers vſed it in the prymatiue churche alſo, folowynge the Lordes commaundemente her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and holden no Maſſe wythout there were ſome that woulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the ſacramente together with the prieſt. Wherefore it muſte nedes be an errour vnlawful to do the contrarie.</p>
               <p>Well thus haue ye hearde a playne declaratyon bothe by the ordynaunce of Chriſte, and by the vſe of the prymatyue churche alſo, that there oughte no Meſſe to be
<pb facs="tcp:11356:76"/> ſayd wherin the ſouper of the lord is handled, without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is to ſay, ſome ſuche as wyll receiue the ſacrament together with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt And nowe to declare alſo that ther ought to be no mo maſſes then one in a churche at ones, ye ſhall firſte con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſydre the worde of god, geuen vs thorow the holy apoſtle Paule, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he ſaieth thus: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye come togethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do not eate the ſouper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord for euery man taketh of the meat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his owne ſouper for him ſelfe.<note place="margin">Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we holde more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we do not holde the ſouper of the lord.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holde, he called it here not the eatin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the lordes ſouper, when euery m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eateth a ſouper for him ſelfe. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vpon, after he had ſet forth the exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple and commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the lord as how he had holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his holy ſoup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him ſelfe, and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded it of othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be holden: and after he had mad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mencion alſo of the great punyſſhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes whiche god had ſente vpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Corinthians for their holding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11356:76"/> the holy ſouper without godly ordre, he concluded with theſe wordes: ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore my brethren, when ye come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to eate, tarye one for another. Nowe yf this be the righte ordre of holding the lordes ſouper, for one to tary ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tely for another, and that the holy ſouper is not kept after a dewe ordre, when there is kept in one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation more than one ſouper at ones, than may euery man wel know that it is a thing vnlawfull ſo to do. And therfore was it a thing vnherd of by them of the olde tyme alſo, than in one churche there ſhould be more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one alter, or that there ſhould be more than one ſouper kept together. Howe ofte dothe ſayncte Cypryane, when he ſpeaketh of the vnyte of the churche, brynge in the one alter, lyke as it is of the other olde fathers alſo?</p>
               <p>Yet is it trew alſo, that at ſuche tyme as the churches were yet but
<pb facs="tcp:11356:77"/> ſmall, and coulde not conuenientlye receyue the people that were for to come together in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">They haue hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den in one churche more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one meſſe vpon a day, but not for all one &amp; the ſame people, but for a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother ſorte of them.</note> that the good holy fathers, haue at hie feaſtes, hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den in one churche mo meſſes than one, but alwayes one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and euery one of them for a parte of the people whiche could not well come to the holy ſouper before. Lyke as we haue a plaine inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this by pope Leo, wrytyng <hi>ad Dioſcorum Alexandrinum</hi> &amp; therof ther is ſumwhat ſpoken alſo, <hi>de conſecrat. diſtinc.</hi> i. cap. <hi>neceſſe.</hi> And therfore the contrary is not to be thoughte, but that al thei that came to any of theſe meſſes, and dyd abyde by the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng of the holy ſouper in them, dyd receyue alſo the ſacrament all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they myghte ſhewe therby they wolde be all of one mynde, wyl, and power, lyke as they had al toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taken parte of one ſacramental breade. And vnto thys receyuyng of
<pb facs="tcp:11356:77"/> the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t together dyd ſaint Am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>broſe exhorte the people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to the maſſe, ſaying:<note place="margin">The peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple vſed in thoſe dayes to bryng theyr of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feringes of bread &amp; wyne vnto the churche and to laye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon the alter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtre myghte geue god thankes for them and ſo diſtry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bute the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the poore: of the why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che there was one portion reſerued for the ſacra. al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo. And bycauſe of this vſe, the Maſſe was ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyce.</note> the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red gyftes, layde vpon the alter for the poore folke, ſhall be of the hole folke: for thorow one bread they are all ſignified, bycauſe that we beyng one, do eate all of one breade. And euen vnto this vniforme maner dyd ſaint Paule exhorte the people alſo when he ſayd: We many are one breade and one bodye. For we all, (although euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet in his owne place, or in the ſame congregation that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth into) do alwaye take parte of one bread in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſouper.</p>
               <p>And further, ſeyng the prieſt in the myniſtration or handlyng of the holy ſouper, ſhall repreſent &amp; ſhewe Chriſte oure Lorde, and that all the praiers made in one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal go together as out of one mouthe &amp; herte, and fynally ſeyng that Chriſt ordeyned thys his holy ſouper to be
<pb facs="tcp:11356:78"/> kepe together of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, which vſe the holy apoſtles deliuered vnto the churche, and the olde churche of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Martiers and Confeſſours haue kept it none otherwyſe, what godly occaſyon than can there be ymagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, wherefore men ſhoulde in one church, and in one congregation of the faythfull, ſpecyally where all they that are preſent may heare well one prieſte, and at one alter receyue the ſacra. to gether, holde mo Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes than one at ones? But all thys notwithſtandynge, after the Pope had broughte in that <hi>Dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <hi>nobiſcum</hi>
                  </hi> ſhoulde be ſongen in Latine to the people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnderſtode it not, then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the prieſtes to paſſe litle whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the people toke any hede to the anſweryng to it or no, ſo they might haue a lyuynge thereby: &amp; after the prieſtes had perſwaded the people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if they ſaw y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacra. lifted vp in the Maſſe, it was euen as good as yf
<pb facs="tcp:11356:78"/> they had examyned their conſcience and come to the receyuyng of it, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came it to paſſe by and by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude of Meſſes were brought vp, to the great deſtruction not onely of the holy ſouper of the Lorde, but of the chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people alſo. For the poore ſimple people beganne then to put theyr truſt in the ſeyng and hearing of Maſſe, withoute anye faythe in Chriſte, and withoute repentaunce for their ſynnes, gathered by the ſame. And that they ſo did maye ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely be peceyued. For howe ſhoulde they eyther haue gathered a ſure fayth in Chriſte by ſeynge the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment (as it was thought to be) to be lyfted vp, when they knew no thing whether it was Chriſtes wyll and mynde to haue it ſo ſhewed vnto theym, or no? wythoute the ſure knoweledge of the whyche, there can no manne, gather a ſure faythe. Or howe ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:11356:79"/> they haue gathered any trewe repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taunce by the hearyng of a prieſt ſay maſſe before them, when they hearde hym ſpeake neuer a worde agaynſt them that brake the lawes of God, wherout the trew knowledge of ſyn and repentaunce for the ſame doeth alwayes ſprynge: ſeyng he ſpake in ſuch a language as they vnderſtode nothyng at all. And therfore it dyd rather co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte them in theyr ſynnes, then moue them from them, ſo longe as it dyd not bryng them trewly vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to theſe .ii. thynges.</p>
               <p>Well, we haue declared thus both theſe .ii. thynges, to wete, fyrſt, that there ought no maſſe to be ſaid, wherin the ſouper of the Lorde is handled, wythout co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municantes. And ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly that there ought no mo maſſes to be ſayde in a churche then one at ones, yf the people may al to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueniently heare one prieſt. And ſo there reſteth to declare nowe,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:79"/> whether it be worthy reprofe &amp; puni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhement for a trewe chriſten man to be preſent at the ſouper of the lorde, and not to receyue the ſacrament.</p>
               <p>The worde of god is doutleſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyfeſt ynough in this, whyche to all them indifferently y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are preſent at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouper is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus in the name of the lorde Chriſte: take, eate, thys is my bodye: take, drynke, thys is my blode. Now to be preſent at the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng of theſe wordes &amp; to geue no credence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt doth offre &amp; preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto vs in them, together wyth the ſacra. the very meat &amp; drinke of euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting life,<note place="margin">It is a playne token of vnfayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fulneſſe and dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at the ſouper &amp; not to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue the ſacra.</note> is ſurely worthy to be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proued in a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But it is not poſſible that we ſhoulde beleue thys trewly &amp; yet not be obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto the lorde in receyuyng at hys ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thankefulneſſe &amp; deuotion ſuche meate and drynke as may geue hym euerlaſtyng lyfe, when it is frely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred hym. And therfore yf not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue
<pb facs="tcp:11356:80"/> that Chriſte doth offre vs here his bodye and blode as the meate of euerlaſtinge lyfe be worthy reproffe, ſo muſt it alſo be worthy reproffe not to take it whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is frely offered. And yf thou ſayeſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art not at all tymes worthy to receyue it when thou art at it, ſo do I aunſwer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> againe, that thou art not worthy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be preſent at it neither. For it is alſo worthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profe for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to geue him ſelfe vnto any godly exerciſe,<note place="margin">To the ſouper perteyne they onely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue.</note> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe not mete or worthy, but ſpecially to be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exercyſing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly ſouper. For it is manifeſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt hylde this his holye ſouper w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch diſciples only as wer worthy (as it appered outwardly, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which we muſt iudge) &amp; as vnto al the whiche he gaue his bodye and blode, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame to take &amp; eate it. Therfore can no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or is mete to be at this godly ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>erciſe, which knoweth not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maye
<pb facs="tcp:11356:80"/> receyue the h. ſacra. to hys ſaluation and ſo be a diſciple Chriſt. For he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath not geuen hym ſelfe ſo farre in to the doctrine of Chriſt, that he wil abyde in the lorde &amp; deſyre the lorde to abyde in hym, he is not mete to heare theſe wordes ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him: take, eat, this is my body. &amp;c.<note place="margin">The holy fathers woulde ſuffer no man to be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſouper whome they thought not mete to receiue</note> Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the h. fathers of olde tyme haue kepte thys vſe very ſtrongely &amp; ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune prayer &amp; ſermone was made, &amp; before they bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to holde the h. ſouꝑ, wolde put out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyng aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſembled together in the churche, not onely ſuche as were yet learners of theyr fayth &amp; not chriſtened, whome they called <hi>Cathecumeni,</hi> and ſuch as were poſſeſſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euel ſprites &amp; were not wel by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues or by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprit of chriſt, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei called <hi>Euergumeni,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in any open crimes or manifeſt vngodlines, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo which ſtode yet in doi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11356:81"/> penaunce whiche had ben layde vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them for theyr great offences, wherwith they had offended y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten congregation openly, and were not yet reconſyled vnto Chriſte, by ſatyſfyenge of his faithfull people whome they had offended, that they would amende, nor abſolued of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the ſame. All theſe they woulde put out of the churche when they woulde holde the holy ſouper of the lorde, as men vnworthye to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at it. Whiche thinge they dyd not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a good cauſe. For ſeyinge Chriſt (as I haue ſayde,) dyd holde this his holy feaſt, with thoſe dyſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, only to all the whiche he gaue his body and blode, and al the which dyd rceiue &amp; eate the ſame: and ſeyng he hath commaunded vs to do euen the ſame thinge in his holy ſouper that he dyd hym ſelfe, ſo is it dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ryghte ſemyng that we ſhoulde holde this holy feaſt but in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence
<pb facs="tcp:11356:81"/> of ſuch dyſciples only (ſo farre forth as we can iudge them by theyr workes) as are both mete, worthye, and deſirous to receyue the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. For as it is very vnmete &amp; worthye great reprofe, as holy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome ſaieth, to be called of a right gracyouſe lorde for to come vnto a coſtly and precyous feaſt, and yet when thou commeſt vnto it not to proue of the meate and drynke that is ſet before the, ſo muſte it nedes be worthy great reprofe to be called of thy lorde and ſauiour, and that to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſtfull eatynge of his moſt precy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous body and blode, and yet not to proue ones of it. And bicauſe of this the holy fathers haue acknowledged all them to be vnworthye alſo to be preſent at the holy ſouper and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the godly miniſtracion therof, that are not worthye and mete to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the holy ſacrament alſo.</p>
               <p>Whiche vnmeteneſſe, vnfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:82"/> and deſpyſyng of the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meate and drynke, holye Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome doeth ſore ſpeake agaynſt in wrytyng thus of it. Who ſo abydeth and ſtandeth preſent at the holy ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, &amp; doth not wyth other receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacramente, he ſtandeth there ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnly and wythout all ſhame. For (ſayeth he) as by the table of a lorde whych is but a man, the ſeruauntes ſhall not be preſent that haue made angrye or offended theyr maiſter, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo ſhall there be done alſo by the holy ſouper, where there is brought forth the kylled offeryng, the Lorde Chriſt, the lambe of God. Therfore men do bydde them go theyr waye that are in ſynne: Now when this is done, and they that knowe them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in ſynne, do not go theyr waye, thei ſhewe therwith an vnſhamefaſt ſtubburneſſe, &amp; ſhal heare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde theſe wordes: Frende, how arte thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men herin. And haſt not the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
<pb facs="tcp:11356:82"/> cloth on? &amp;c. And thys h. doctor Chriſoſtome noteth theſe wordes ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciallye here, that the lorde ſayd not: Wherfore art thou ſytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe, but wherfore art y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men herin. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he wolde ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhulde no man come in or tarye at thys feaſt, whych is not clothed with the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age cloth Chriſt, that is to ſay, which is not mete to receyue holſomely the holy ſacra. to his ſaluation. But yf it be ſo, that a man do not know him ſelfe to be in wylful ſynne, that is to ſay, that he wyl wylfully abyde in it, when he is preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouper, ſo wer it then a great ſhame to deſpyſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne the kyng our lorde Chriſt, &amp; his heuenly meate &amp; drynke, in not receyuyng it whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſo gentely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered. And ſuche a one doeth Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome compare to hym that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyred of a frende to a good ſouper, and commeth, waſſheth hys handes, and lytteth downe at the table, and
<pb facs="tcp:11356:83"/> yet toucheth nothyng, nor ones pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth of the meate: whome doutleſſe (ſayth he) he that deſired ſuch a one, can do none other then take hym vp agayne to hys great ſhame.</p>
               <p>Thys holy father geueth this an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſwere alſo vnto al them that wyl ſay they are vnmete or vnworthy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the ſacrament,<note place="margin">He that is not mete to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munyon of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament is not mete to praye to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether with the churche.</note> and wyll yet be preſent at the holy ſouper. He that is not mete to receiue the ſacrament, is neither mete wyth the churche to praye nor ones to beholde the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But he ſhall do penance fyrſt, and then come vnto the table of the lorde, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he fyndeth hym ſelfe mete to receyue the holy ſacrament alſo.</p>
               <p>And thys ordinaunce dyd Pope Calixtius acknowledge to haue ben receyued of the Apoſtles &amp; to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in his tyme in the churche of Rome,<note place="margin">e. ꝑacta. de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſec. diſtinc. xi.</note> as he witneſſed ſaying. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the halowyng and preparyng of the people to the ſacrament by thankes
<pb facs="tcp:11356:83"/> geuynge vnto the Lorde for it,<note place="margin">Thapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned that ſuche ſhoulde be ſhette out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche, as wold not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune.</note> is done, then ſhall they all be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nycated, that wyll not be ſhett out of the churche. For thus (ſaieth he) haue the Apoſtles ordeyned it, and thus doth the church of Rome kepe it. What woulde thys Pope ſaye (thynke you) yf he myght now come into the church of Rome and ſee the ſacramente (as it is thought to be) handled in euery corner of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, and yet neyther the prieſtes to offre it vnto any man, nor any of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ones to deſire it? woulde he ſaye that this Pope were ether hys ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor or the ſucceſſore of thapoſtles? no truly. For yf he thought it to be a godly ordynaunce and worthie to be kepte of all men ones, and that ſo muche the more as it had ben vſed of thapoſtles them ſelues, that all they ſhould be ſhet out of the church, that would not receyue the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſouper of the lorde was kepte, he
<pb facs="tcp:11356:84"/> would doutleſſe the ſay both y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this were not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> keping of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right ſouper of the lorde whiche is nowe vſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, &amp; alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which was now Pope, were no true Chriſten man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſtinc. i.</note>The .ix. cannon alſo which Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus witneſſeth to haue ben the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of thapoſtles, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all faithfull that come into the churche and heare the ſcripture, yf they wil not alſo continue in praieng and receyuyng of the ſacramente, to be ſhet out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, as them that ſet vp a myſordre amongeſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. Whiche thing was ordeyned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the .ii. canon <hi>concilii Antiochini.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the .viii. canon of thapoſtles doth require, that yf a biſhop, prieſt, deacon, or other clerke wyll not be communicated when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouper of the lorde is holden, he ſhoulde ſhewe the cauſe therof. And yf the cauſe be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, he ſhould be pardoned, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he dyd not communicate. But yf he do not
<pb facs="tcp:11356:84"/> ſhew the cauſe of it, ſo ſhal he be ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out of the congregacion, as one that offendeth the people, and ſtyrreth vp a ſuſpection of him that offered the ſacrament to be receyued.</p>
               <p>Now theſe .iii. canons or holy or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynaunces do acknowledge it to be ſo great a faute, to come into the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gregation where the holy ſouper of the lorde is holden, and yet not to be communicated, that they commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſuch to be excluded and ſhet out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche. Shewinge this to be the cauſe of their appoyntinge ſo harde a puniſhement to the offenders. By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they that dyd ſo abſteyne or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hold themſelues, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dyd brynge in a myſordre into the church. As yf it wer don of a biſhop, prieſt, deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or other clerke, it cauſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to ſuſpect his liuing or lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, which dyd miniſtre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacra. to beſuch, as w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>municated. For who ſo did not holde
<pb facs="tcp:11356:85"/> hym ſelfe in the trew doctrine recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and agreed vpon in the churche (as there were many ſuche in thoſe dayes) with him dyd no deuout byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope, pryeſt or clerke, communicate. He ſhall therefore (ſayth the canon) ſhewe the cauſe, why he is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, &amp; not bring in, or ſtyre vp a vayne ſuſpectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thorow the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy miniſtracion might be deſpyſed, or a deuyſyon ſet vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the people.</p>
               <p>Who ſeeth not now by theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that to appere by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſouper, and not to be communicated w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the congregracion, hath ben condemned both in laye men and alſo in the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye. And that therfore, bycauſe it brought in a miſordre amongeſt the people whiche were in vſe to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated together.</p>
               <p>But ſpecially we may ſee by this latter canon, that al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people in thoſe dayes when this ordre was taken,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:85"/> dyd vſe to be communicated toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; that ſuche ſhould be expulſed as would not come to the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. For elles how ſhoulde that miniſtre haue ben brought in an euel ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion with the people, that miniſtred the holy ſouper, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a byſhop, prieſt, deacon or other clerke had come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in and not ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated with him at his miniſtracion, yf it had not ben the commen vſe that all they whiche were preſent at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſouper ſhould be communicated? and in lyke man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, how ſhould they of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> layte which dyd not receiue it together, haue ben accuſed therof, as men that ſet vp a miſordre in the churche, yf it had not ben the commen vſe, that when the holy ſouper was holden, al they that were preſent ſhoulde receyue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramente together? but doutleſſe it was the commen ordre in thoſe day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, that men ſhoulde ſhet out of the churche and commen congregation
<pb facs="tcp:11356:86"/> bothe them of the clergye and laite, that were preſent at the holy ſouper, and were not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated together. And that for this purpoſe, bycauſe the doynge therof, when it was done of a laye man, dyd bryng in a miſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre in the churche where the people were wont to receyue the ſacramente all together: and when it was done of any of the clergye it ſtirred vp an euell ſuſpection towardes him that miniſtred the holy ſouper.</p>
               <p>Out of al theſe now it is manifeſt and plaine to euery chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that both after the worde of god, and vſe of the olde or prymatyue churche, it was worthy reprofe, to be preſent at the holy ſouper, and not to receyue the ſacrament together. For the lord hath ordeyned his holy ſouper, for al them his diſciples only, that wyl and maye receiue it together. And he that wyll not be ſuche a dyſciple, to him is not this ſouper prepared. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord
<pb facs="tcp:11356:86"/> hath not inſtituted it to be a lokyng glaſſe, or a gaſyng ſtocke, but ſayde: take, eate: take &amp; drynke. And lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Paule: the breade y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we breake, &amp;c. we, ſaith he, &amp; not I,<note place="margin">Cor. xi.</note> or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prieſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. And further ſaith he: one bread one body, for we all take part of one bread: we al, ſayth he. And thus hath the olde churche vſed it alſo, tyll the true gouerning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame dyd fall, &amp; tyll men bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to holde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> h. ſouper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, not therto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more perfiteli liue in chriſt, &amp; he in vs, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prieſtes might get the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a liuing by it, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any true teaching or pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching of Chriſt, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ani mouing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of liuing by their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dlyng of the h. ſacra. Which thing to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better, the prieſtes ſaid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe was a ſacrifice for ſin. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to loke at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacra. a farre of, bycauſe the prieſtes had perſwaded theym, that yf they were preſente at the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge and ſeynge of the Maſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:11356:87"/> or gaue any thing therunto, ſo ſhuld it obteyne them al good fortune, and ſaue them from all peryll &amp; dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. whether they vnderſtode it, or not, whether thei were communicated or not, they hauynge repentaunce for their ſinnes and purpoſe to amende there lyues, or not. But as god and our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt, hath ordei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned this holy ſacrament for to moue vs firſt vnto a ſure faith and truſte in the free remyſſion of our ſynnes, that he might the better ſo, cauſe vs bothe to repent of our ſynful lyues, and to be bolde alſo to folowe his moſte louynge commaundementes, and that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtring of his ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed body and blode to be receyued of vs by the corporall receyuing of it: he graunt vs alſo ſo to behaue oure ſelues at all ſuche times as it ſhalbe preſented vnto vs, that we maye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynually be thankefull bothe to him and to our neyghboure for the ſame.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11356:87" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>Graunte this, good Lorde, for thy ſwete ſonnes ſake Ieſus Chriſte. Amen. </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Gawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Lynne dwellyng on So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers kaye by Byl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges gate.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
